<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A preparation into the waye of lyfe vvith a direction into the right vse of the Lords Supper: gathered by VVilliam Hopkinson, preacher of the worde of God.</title>
            <author>Hopkinson, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855554</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855554</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21049</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03645)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21049)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 639:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A preparation into the waye of lyfe vvith a direction into the right vse of the Lords Supper: gathered by VVilliam Hopkinson, preacher of the worde of God.</title>
                  <author>Hopkinson, William.</author>
                  <author>Dering, Edward, 1540?-1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Walde-graue, for Iohn Harrison the yonger, and Thomas Manne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A most godly and comfortable letter, written by maister Edvvard Deering, to a christian gentlevvoman, beeing in heauinesse of spirit" has caption title on D8v.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Preparation into the waye of lyfe, vvith a direction into the right vſe of the Lords Supper: Gathered by VVilliam Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon, Preacher of the worde of God.</p>
            <p>Printed at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, by Robert Walde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, for Iohn Harriſon the yonger, and Thomas Manne. 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>To the right Honorable</hi> Syr Henry Sidney, Lorde Preſident of <hi>her Maiesties Counſel in the Marches</hi> of VVales, Knight of the moſte noble order of the Garter, and of her Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Counſell: VV. H. wiſheth plentie of thoſe bleſſings which haue promiſes of this life and the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing that it is the duetie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery true Chriſtian (Righte Honorable) from the higheſt to the loweſt, according to the meaſure of the grace that he hath receyued of the Lord, to reache out him ſelfe vvith continuall attendance to profite euery his felowe neighbour, eſpecially in the charge ouer vvhiche the Lorde hath ſet him for the tyme, ſo labouring in him ſelfe to exceede the meaſure of the moſte, vvho make muche of lyfe vvithout conſideration vvherefore they liue: I haue held my ſelfe boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:3"/>by all meanes that I might, to endeuour the regarde of thoſe ouer vvhom the Lorde by your Honour hath ſet me. And ſeeing that not onely the iudgement of reaſon, but continuall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth teache vs, that to make a ſcholler lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the tongues, the readyeſt vvay is, to begin vvith the letters, or vvell profited in any Science, to ſet firſt a ſure foundation in the principles of the ſame, I haue helde it the moſte ready en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce to make the Lordes trueth familiar to his people, eſpecially them of vvhom I haue ſpeciall knowledge, and ouer vvhom peculiar charge, to laye the groundworke as ſure as I might, namely in leading them in the light of the Lords vvorde, to the true ſight of them ſelues in two reſpectes, that is, vvhat they are by nature, and vvhat by grace, vvherof if eyther be vvanting in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſtians, the Lorde looſeth (in reſpect of him) his due glory, and the people their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. As if the firſt be not knowen, men receiue the Lordes promiſes in ſecuritie, as vvhich num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at this day ſeemeth to be great, and if the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond be not had, mens hearts are ſurpriſed in the vvaye of death. And as he that buyldeth without a foundation layde, ſhall buylde in the ayrc, ſo this ſteddie groundworke ſurely founded, &amp; vvell beat vpon, ſhall giue an eaſie entraunce to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buylding by the vvord of doctrine and faith, that the Lordes Saintes by this meanes maye through his grace not onely be gathered, as the Apoſtle ſayth, but that through the vvorke of the miniſtery they may be built vp into him vvhich
<pb facs="tcp:21049:3"/>is the head, euen Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe I haue, as I might, gathered theſe directions by the Lords vvorde, for a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall teſtimony to remayne vvith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a conſent to ſuche as turne to the Lorde, and for a vvitneſſe to the reſt. But eſpecially (next vnto this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation layde) haue I laboured to leade them into the right vſe of the Lords Supper, a ſpeciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Gods promiſes in Chriſt to our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, a matter alſo miſerably neglected and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accounted of, to the lamentable ruine and downefall of many thouſande ſoules, for the Lordes iudgementes ſtande inuiolably: vvhoſe vvorkes doth teſtifie that they are iuſtly in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his endles indignation, vvho prophane his miſteries in vnworthines, of vvhat condition or ſort ſoeuer they be, for vvith him is no reſpect of perſons. In both vvhich I haue ioyned the deſire of mine owne diſcharge, vvith the peoples ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and gathered the ſumme of both into ſuche a forme, as may beſt agree vvith their experience: not as refuſing or lightly accouting of the labors of ſuch godly brethren as haue much profited the Lords people in the lyke vvay, but as caſting in two mytes vvith the poore VVidow to the Lotds vvorke, vvhich as it vvas ſpecially ment for mine owne charge, ſo haue I yeelded to the perſwaſion of certayne godly friendes, to communicate the ſame vvith the Church of God by ſuffering it to be publiſhed in print, both for the comfort of the godly, the Lorde bleſſing it: and teſtifie to the Papiſtes the Lordes enimies, that though the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of ſpeach be diuers, yet that vvee holde
<pb facs="tcp:21049:4"/>firmely one and the ſelfe ſame grounde and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of trueth, and that there is not amongſt vs at all any oddes or varietie of doctrine, vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they and their lyke, ſhame not vniuſtly to ſay agaynſt vs.</p>
            <p>But in this caſe conſidering that it muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe the viewe aſwell of foes as fauourers, &amp; that as I am aſſured of fauourable acceptation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the godly, yet as the ſunne neuer vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth light, the fyre heate, or the ſroſtie vvynter coldnes: ſo haue there euer bene, and vvyll be, plentie of ſuch vvho in ſteade of vvell deſeruing, do pleaſe them ſelues vvith vniuſt reproching of others labours. In this reſpect, as that I might content my ſelfe, in accepting gladly any iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to leaue ſome teſtimonie of a right thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart for your Honours fauours many wayes vouchſafed me, vvhereby I holde my ſelfe in the Lorde continually bounde to your Honorable houſe in all that I maye, and in conſideration vvherof, vvhen other meanes be vvanting wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to teſtifie the ſame, I ſhall not ceaſe (I truſte) right humbly to commende your eſtate vnto the Lorde, vvho hath promiſed to heare the iuſte prayers of his ſeruauntes for the vvorthines of his Chriſt: So haue I bene bolde to preſent the ſame vnto your Honour, ſuch as it is, the rather hauing iuſt cauſe to perſwade my ſelfe of your honorable acceptation and protection of vvhatſoeuer may profite the Church of God, I haue alſo together deliuered to the print, for the care I haue of my brethrens health, a moſt notable and chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable letter, vvritten by that notable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:21049:4"/>of the Church of God in his time, M. Edward Dering, to a godly chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by which through the Lordes bleſſing I muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to haue gayned muche comfort, as alſo mine hartie deſire and hope is that others ſhall. So that vvhile the vncleane and impure Atheiſtes, frozen harted Papiſtes, temporiſers, carnall Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, and infidels, ſhall ſuppe out the meaſure of Gods iudgementes to the bottome, vve, vvell vvarranted in our Chriſtian eſtate, ſoundly dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the right vſe of the Lordes myſteries, by the vvorde preſerued in the extremities of ſinne, and in all, lightned to the right application of the grace of Chriſt, ſhall vvith inuincible conſtancie runne out the courſe that is ſet before vs, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently vvayte for our deliueraunce, euen the comming of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, of vvhom it is vvritten that he ſhall appeare the ſeconde time vvithout ſinne to ſaluation, to them that vvayte for him. VVhich that vve maye conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually do, our good God and Father graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by the ſpeciall direction of his holy ſpirite of ſanctification and grace, and powre plentifully vpon your Honour thoſe bleſſings vvhich ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye concerne the aduauncement of his glory, your Honours ſafetie both in body and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the peace of his Church, in and for his ſonne our Lorde Ieſus. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humbly to be alwayes vſed in the Lorde Chriſte, VVILLIAM HOPKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:5"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A preparation into the waye of lyfe: with a direction into the right vſe of the Lords Supper.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe had you your beeing at the firſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> God created mee and all men in Adam, as it is written, The Lorde God made man of the duſte of the grounde, and breathed in his face breath of life, and man was made a liuing ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi> Wherefore did God create you?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſeeke his glory, as it is written, Of him, through him, and for him are all things, to him be glory for euer. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu</hi> How will God be glorified?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> According to his will reuealed in his worde. For it is written:
<note place="margin">Deut. 12.32.</note> Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:21049:6"/>I commaunde you, take heede that you doe it, thou ſhalt put nothing thereto, nor take ought therefrom. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> In what eſtate were you created?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Holy and excellent, without ſinne, in perfect righteouſnes and holynes before him, as appeareth <hi>Gen.</hi> Let vs make man in our image according to our likenes,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> How became you ſubiect to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny infirmities?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By ſinne and diſobedience. As it is written: Becauſe thou haſte obeyed the voyce of thy wife, and haſt eaten of the tree wherof I commaunded thee,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.17.</note> ſaying: Thou ſhalt not eate of it: curſed is the earth for thy ſake, in ſorrow ſhalt thou eate of it all the dayes of thy life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> How became you ſinnefull?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Adam tranſgreſſed the Lords pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in eating the forbidden fruite, loſt his innocencie, and brought ſinne vpon him ſelf and all his poſteritie. As appeareth when he had yeelded to diſobey the Lorde.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.9.10.</note> The Lorde God called to the man, and ſayde to him, Where art thou? Who ſaid, I heard thy voyce, and was afraide, becauſe I was naked, therefore I hidde my ſelfe. Alſo the
<pb facs="tcp:21049:6"/>Lorde God ſent him foorth from the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Eden,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.23.</note> to till the earth from whence he was taken. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Is this ſinne in euery one by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yea in all Adams poſteritie, none excepted: as it is written,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> As by one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo death went ouer all men, in as much as all men haue ſinned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the rewarde of ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Death eternall: as it is written,
<note place="margin">Deut. 27.26.</note> Curſed bee hee that continueth not in all the wordes of this lawe, to doe them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Shall I eſcape this death by the workes of the lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No. For it is written,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> For that that was impoſſible to the law, in as much as it was not able becauſe of the fleſh, God ſending his owne ſonne in the ſimiſitude of ſinnefull fleſh condemned ſinne in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Sith the Lawe doth not inſtifie vs before God, what profite hath a Chriſtian by it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The vſe of the lawe. Ioſh. 1.8.</note> Firſt it is a way for Gods children to walke in: as it is written, Let not this
<pb facs="tcp:21049:7"/>booke of the lawe depart out of thy mouth, but meditate therein day and night, that thou mayeſt obſerue and doe according to all that is written therein, for then ſhalte thou make thy waye proſperous, and then ſhalt thou haue good ſucceſſe. &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6. Secondly, it teacheth man not to truſte in his owne innocencie. For it is written, We haue proued that all both Iewes and Gentiles are vnder ſinne.
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.9.</note> 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1.53.4. Thirdly, it pulleth downe the pride of mans heart, and humbleth him before God: as it is written, We knowe that whatſoeuer the lawe ſayth, it ſayth it to them which are vnder the lawe, that euery mouth may be ſtopped,
<note place="margin">Ro. 3.19.20.</note> and all the world culpable before God. And by the workes of the lawe ſhall no fleſhe be iuſtified, for by the lawe commeth the knowledge of ſinne. Fourthly, it is a ſcholemaiſter to Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.23.</note> for it is written, Before faith came we were kept vnder the lawe, and ſhut vp vnto the fayth that ſhould afterwardes be reuealed, wherefore the lawe was oure ſcholemaſter to bring vs vnto Chriſt, that we might be made righteous by fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Why ſhould we doe good workes,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:7"/>ſithe they do not iuſtifie vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt,
<note place="margin">The right end of workes. Ioh. 14.15.</note> to ſhewe our loue to God our father, in walking as becommeth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. For the Lorde ſayth, If you loue me keepe my commaundementes. <hi>Leui.</hi> 11.44.19.2. Secondly, to ſhewe our loue to our ſelues, making our election therby ſure vnto our ſelues. For it is written.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.3.4.</note> Bleſſed be God, euen the father of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. &amp;c. He hath choſen vs in him before the foundation of the worlde was layde, that we ſhould be holy and without blame before him in loue. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. Thirdly, to profite our brethren, and glorifie the Lorde.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing your good workes, maye glorifie your father which is in heauen. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">VVhat works be good, and the contrary. Rom 14.23.</note> Howe many things are principally to be conſidered in good workes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Three. Firſt, that they proceede from an heart purified by fayth. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is not of fayth, is ſinne. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.17.18. Secondly, they muſte be ruled by the worde of God: for it is written,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> We are his workmanſhip created in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good workes, which he hath prepared
<pb facs="tcp:21049:8"/>for vs to walke in. Thirdly, the ſpeciall ende for which they are done muſte be the glory of God:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31</note> for it is written, Whether you eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer you doe, doe all to the glory of God. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is eternall death?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The euerlaſting curſe of God, whiche conteineth all the tormentes that can be deuiſed both of ſoule and body: for it is written,
<note place="margin">Deut. 27.26.</note> Curſed is he that continueth not in all the wordes of this lawe to doe them. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> By what meanes ſhall I eſcape this death?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Onely by fayth in Chriſt: as it is written,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.28.</note> We conclude that a man is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by fayth, without the workes of the lawe. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.13, 36. 5.24. 6.40, 47. 11.25. 20.29, 31. <hi>Math.</hi> 9.2, <hi>Luc.</hi> 7.50. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. 16.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is a Chriſtian fayth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">VVhat fayth is.</note> A full perſwaſion and aſſurance of mine heart, that whatſoeuer Chriſte hath wrought for mans ſaluation, perteineth
<pb facs="tcp:21049:8"/>not onely to others, but to me alſo, and is furely mine: as it is written, For I am perſwaded that neither death for life,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lorde. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Shall all men be ſaued by Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No. None but they onely that do in deede beleeue in him. For it is written,
<note place="margin">To whom the death of Chriſt is profitable.</note> He that beleeueth in the ſonne hath life, and he that beleeueth not in the ſonne hath not life. And, he that beleeueth not is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned already, becauſe he beleeueth not. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.24. 6.47.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> How do we attayne to fayth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The holy Ghoſt worketh it in our hearts. As Eſay teſtifieth of the Churche,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 54.13.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aying, they ſhal be all taught of the Lord. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8, 6.23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3.3.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2. 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Iob.</hi> 6.44, 45.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> By what meanes?
<note place="margin">The neceſſitie of the words preached.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By hearing the word preached: as is written, Faith is by hearing,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:21049:9"/>by the worde of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> May not this hearing be as well by reading, as by the preaching of the worde?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No. For it is written, Howe can they heare without a preacher.
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> May euery one preach that liſte?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> No. For it is written, Howe ſhall they preach, except the Lorde ſende them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What teſtimonie can be had of any whether he be ſent of the Lorde in this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for you knowe it is an eaſie matter to pretende a ſending?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Beſides an ordinarie calling of the Church wherein he liueth, he muſte of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie haue <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thumin,</hi> knowledge and holynes, he muſt be, as it is written, wiſe, righteous, holy, temperate, holding faſte the faythfull worde according to doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that he alſo may be able to exhorte with wholſome doctrine,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.8, 9.</note> and improue them that ſay againſt it. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.3. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Do you holde it conuenient that euery miniſter of the worde and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes be a preacher?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yea eſpecially. For the Lorde is the fulneſſe of all wiſedome, and ſendeth
<pb facs="tcp:21049:9"/>only ſuch as by his grace haue to diſpatch his meſſage, alſo he ſending forth his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſaide, goe preach the Goſpell &amp;c. and to ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neceſſitie of preaching, he ſaith to Peter. Feede, feede, feede, Acts, 20.28 1. Cor. 3.5. 1. Cori. 4.1. 2. Cor. 3.6. Ephe. 3.7. Col. 1.7.1. Tim. 4.6.1. Per. 5.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Do you thinke it needefull to haue in euerie congregation a miniſter that is apte to teach?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yea, moſt needefull, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, wher there is no preaching, the people periſhe. Alſo the Apoſtles in the wiſdome of the holie ghoſt (beyonde which we may not preſume) ordeined ſuche in euerie Church,
<note place="margin">Acts. 14.23. Tit. 1.5.</note> and Paul appointed Titus to do the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Do you not think it ſufficient that the people do heare the worde preached once in a year, or in their life. Though they haue no continuall preacher to labour in the worde amongſt them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No, in no caſe. For as the body can not liue with ſuch nouriſhment,
<note place="margin">The greate neceſſitie of preaching miniſters.</note> muche leſſe the ſoule without continuall comfort from the worde of God our only ſpirituall foode: and there be dayly profitings in Gods
<pb facs="tcp:21049:10"/>Church wherto the Lords miniſters muſt carefully attende. To this effect ſpeaketh Paule to Titus,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> ſaying, For this cauſe left I thee at Creta, that thou ſhouldeſt continue to redreſſe the thinges that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne, &amp;c. Alſo no houſe is buylt ſo ſoone as the firſt ſtone of the foundation is layde, and S. Paule ſheweth the ende for whiche the Lorde doth giue his faythfull ſeruantes his miniſters into his Church, namely, not onely for the gathering togeather and for the worke of the miniſterie, but alſo for the buylding vp the Lords Saints, the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the body of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.12, 14.15.</note> that we might be no more children caried about with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry winde of doctrine, but that we mighte grow vp into him which is the head, that is Chriſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Seeing you thinke it a matter ſo greatly needefull that there be in euery congregation continually a godly miniſter apte to teache, let me (I pray you) heart your iudgement by the word of God what is required of the people concerning them, and the worde which they bring vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is it in their choyce whether they wyll heare their preachers, and any whitte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:21049:10"/>of them, or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No.
<note place="margin">The peoples duety to their paſtours.</note> For as no Prince or maiſter can beare the reiecting of his Ambaſſador or ſeruaunt ſent foorth in ſpeciall meſſage, though to his equals: ſo neither can or will the Lorde beare the like at our hands who be his vaſſals. And to this effect,
<note place="margin">The Lords mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters muſt be receiued.</note> that his faythfull ſeruauntes his miniſters might be comforted agaynſt the vnthankfulneſſe of the world, and to ſet the people out of doubt how he would haue them taken, he ſayth, He that receiueth you receiueth me,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.40.</note> and he that receiueth me receiueth hym that ſent me. Alſo he addeth,
<note place="margin">Luc. 10.16.</note> He that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth you deſpiſeth me, and he that deſpiſeth me deſpiſeth him that ſent me. And to put vs out of doubt in what ſort he would haue vs to receiue his ſeruauntes ſent to vs for our ſuche ſinguler profite, as the ſaluation of our whole ſoule and body,
<note place="margin">They muſt be heard and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed.</note> he doth teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vnto vs in his worde, firſt that we muſt heare and obey them. Secondly, that we muſt nouriſh them: and thirdly, that we muſt eſteeme of them, and laſtly, that we muſt pray for them. For the firſt he ſayth by the Apoſtle S. Paule,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.9.</note> For this cauſe did I write, that I might know the proofe
<pb facs="tcp:21049:11"/>of you, whether you would be obedient in all things. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.4, 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. For the ſecond,
<note place="margin">They muſt be nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for. Gal. 6.6.</note> it is thus written, Let him that is taught in the worde, make him that hath taught him, partaker of al his goods. And alſo we beſeeche you brethren, that you know them that labour among you, and are ouer you in the Lorde, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe you, that you haue them in ſinguler loue for their works ſake. &amp;c. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7, 8, 9.
<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.12 13. They muſt be eſteemed 1. Tim. 5.17.</note> For the thirde it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thus: The Elders that rule well are worthy of double honour, ſpecially they which labour in the worde and doctrine. 3. <hi>Iob.</hi> 8. And for the laſte it is written thus,
<note place="margin">They muſt be prayed for of the faithfull. Col. 4.3.</note> Continue in prayer and watche in the ſame with thankes giuing, praying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for vs, that God may open vnto vs the doore of vtteraunce, to ſpeake the myſterie of Chriſte, &amp;c. that I may vtter it as I ought to ſpeake, &amp;c. And alſo, Brethren pray for vs,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.1.</note> that the worde of the Lorde may haue free paſſage and be glorified. &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> I pray you, how are they accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of before the Lorde which do not theſe dueties, for I thinke you ſhall eaſily finde
<pb facs="tcp:21049:11"/>many which profeſſe the Goſpell, and yet do neuer one of them, but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. So that the very Papiſtes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels receiue more readily, obey more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, prouide for more ſufficiently, eſteme more highly, and do all other things more carefully (as our experience doth approue too true) for their popiſh ſacrificers, idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and diuell worſhippers, then theſe doe, the true ſeruauntes and miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In the Lordes preſence they be found to deceiue them ſelues,
<note place="margin">The ſtate of ſuch as neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ther du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the Lordes meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers. Mat. 7.21.</note> whoſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is but in vayne words, for that the Lord liueth not in them, as in deede he doth not where his glory and kingdome is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for. Of whom the mouth of the Lorde hath ſpoken, that they ſhall neuer enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of heauen, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to periſh in extreme famine, that ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reiect, or ſo lightly account of the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall foode of their ſoules reached vnto them of the Lorde by the handes of hys Church and miniſters, and their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſleepeth not, for the Lorde him ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth, Who ſoeuer ſhall not receiue you, nor heare your wordes, when you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte
<pb facs="tcp:21049:12"/>out of that houſe, or out of that citie, ſhake of the duſt of your feete.
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.14, 15.</note> Truely I ſay vnto you, it ſhall be eaſier for them of the lande of Sodom and Gomortha in the day of iudgement, then for that Citie. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.11, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Many thinke them ſelues in beſt caſe when they haue a miniſter that cannot labour in preaching the worde of the Lord amongeſt them, what do you think of their eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Men miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly blinde and ſee it not.</note> Firſt their eſtate is moſt wretched, for that as blinde men without guide, they wander in darkneſſe, for without the word there is no light in our waies.
<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.105</note> Thy worde is a lanterne to my feete, and a lighte vnto my pathes, and alſo both the one and the other be vnder the iudgement of God.
<note place="margin">Mat. 15.14. The eſtate of the people that haue an vnpreaching miniſter.</note> If the blinde lead the blind, doth they not both fall into the ditche?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Then it ſemeth that you tye the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the people of neceſſitie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It is moſte true, for without the preaching of the Goſpell, there is no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie meane to attaine to faith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by hearing the worde of God prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.
<pb facs="tcp:21049:12"/>Without faith we cannot atteine to Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.40.</note> He that ſeeth the ſonne and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him hath euerlaſting life. &amp;c. With out Chriſt is no way to pacifie the fathers wrath.
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17.</note> This is my beloued ſonne in whom I am well pleaſed, heare him. And if the fathers wrath bee not pacified there is no hope of life,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 2.12.</note> if his wrath be kindled yea but a little we ſhall periſh in the way.
<note place="margin">The neceſſitie of preaching the Goſpell, which men make light of.</note> So that I conclude, that without the preaching of the Goſpell it is not poſſible to be ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Do you include, infants, fooles, and deaf folkes within this neceſſity?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No,
<note place="margin">The wiſdome of Gods ſpirit doth leade vs in the ſtreight wayes of the Lorde.</note> nor binde the Lorde vnto the meane, but in all chinges confeſſe him to be free, but I ſay, that for others, the Lord hath giuen vs no ordinarie meane but the preaching of his Goſpell.
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> Goe preache the Goſpell to all creatures, who ſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth and is baptiſed ſhall bee ſaued. &amp;c. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> There be that thinke, that if a man haue learning,
<note place="margin">Selfeliking, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and reaſon that is corrupt, blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des many a one.</note> eſpecially in the ſciences &amp; tonges, he can not be ignorant of the way of life, and ſo will often reaſon for others, and perſuade them ſelues, the one ſay ſuch bee learned, they muſte needes knowe the
<pb facs="tcp:21049:13"/>truth,
<note place="margin">The wiſdom of carnall men is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. The Lorde when he wil doth vſe the meane, but he is not bounde to it</note> and the other contemne preaching, as if they were too wiſe for it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Albeit it pleaſeth the Lorde to vſe the ciuill knowledge whereof you ſpeake for the furtherance of his goſpel, when one where he ſeeth it conuenient, yet is it no ſure conſequent that where theſe thinges he, there alſo is the ſure knowledge of the Lordes truth, for in Epheſus were many excellentlie learned in ciuill knowledge,
<note place="margin">As Pitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menides, Zeno, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus, &amp; ſuch like. Epheſ. 1.13.</note> and yet wholie ignoraunt of the way of the Lorde, and Saint Paule proueth their faith in Chriſt, to haue commed only from the preaching of the Goſpell thorough the power of the ſpirite of Chriſte, ſaying. In whom ye alſo truſted, after that you heard the worde of truth, euen the goſpel of your ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Then, as I take it, alſo you would that in teaching there ſhould onely be vſed the teſtimonie of the worde it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">The maner of ſuch as ſeeke more to pleaſe their cares then to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite their ſoule.</note> And yet many that goe for wiſe men, do looke that the preachers ſhould feede them with prophane ſtories, and ſayings of men. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſome like to ſpende much time in fables, and other needleſſe matter? Howe thinke you of it?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> I graunt you that ſuch things may carry a wilie ſhew to the carnall man, but in all theſe and a thouſand moe of like ſort, ſtandeth not the faith of Gods choſen, for it onely reſteth in the word of trueth, which Saint Paul teſtifieth in this reſpect,
<note place="margin">Eſai. 55.11.</note> to be the Goſpell, and when theſe be at the laſt, yet want the warrant of the ſpirite to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for them that they be the word of truth. Againe, the Lord bleſſeth his own meane whoſe goſpel hath a bleſſing in it ſelfe, and neuer returneth emptie, which all theſe earthly out ſhowes want, though in ſome ſort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auouching of ſome haue their vſe, namely to confute them that truſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.28. Tit. 5.1.12. 2. Tim 4.2.</note> as S. Paul doth in the like, alſo they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to preach the worde, Mat. 28.20. 1. Pet. 4.11. Iho. 9.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> I ſee then that the onely way to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie vs before God, is through fayth in Ieſus Chriſt, which you proue that God worketh in our hearts by the preaching of his Goſpell. But by what meanes I pray you is this iuſtifying fayth continued and increaſed in vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By the ſelfe ſame preaching of the worde. For as it is written, As new borne
<pb facs="tcp:21049:14"/>babes,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that you may grow thereby. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.13, 14. Alſo the holy Sacramentes are ordeined for vs of the Lord to this end,
<note place="margin">The Lorde by his word and Sacramentes sheweth hys ſinguler care for the ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of his Church. Gal. 3.27.</note> namely to confirme the promiſes of his Goſpell vnto vs, and to confirme our fayth in the ſame. As appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, All ye which are baptized into Ieſus Chriſt, haue put on Chriſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. And,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.51.</note> I am the liuing bread which came downe from heauen, if any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for euer. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Are there no neceſſarie helpes vnto theſe for the increaſe and confirmation of our fayth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yes, and thoſe that can not be wanting without great preiudice to the Church of God: namely true, earneſt and often prayer, and diſcipline according to the worde. As, for the firſt it is ſayde, Aſke and haue, and whatſoeuer you aſke of the father in my name he will giue it you. And for the ſeconde it is written thus,
<note place="margin">Cor. 5 3, 4, 5.</note> I verily as abſent in body but preſent in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riie, haue determined already as though I were preſent, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he that hath thus done this thing, when you are gathered togeather
<pb facs="tcp:21049:14"/>and my ſpirite in the name of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, that ſuche a one, I ſay, by the power of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, be deliuered to Satan for the deſtruction of the fleſhe, that the ſpirite may be ſaued in the day of the Lorde Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is a Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Sacrament what it is.</note> An outward ſigne ordeined of God for the greater aſſurance and ſtrength of our fayth, beeing vnto vs ſure pledges of thoſe veneſites of our ſaluation which we receiue in Chriſt to be ours. For it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.11.</note> Ye ſhall circumcize the foreſkinne of your fleſhe, and it ſhall be a ſigne of the couenaunt betweene me and you. <hi>Exo.</hi> 12.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> How many Sacraments be there in the church of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Two, baptiſme, &amp; the Lords ſupper, as appeareth. Brethren I would not haue you ignorant, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al your fathers were vnder the cloude, and al paſſed through the ſea, &amp; were al baptiſed vnto Moſes in the cloude, and in the ſea,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> and did all eate of the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did all drinke of the ſame ſpiritual drink, for they dranke of the ſpirituall rock that followed them, and the
<pb facs="tcp:21049:15"/>rocke was Chriſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Who ſhall miniſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> He in whoſe mouth the Lorde hath put his worde for the people, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Go teach al nations, baptiſing them in the name of the father, and the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt. Chriſt gaue this commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, neither to midwiues (as they call them) or any other women, or to priuate men, but to thoſe whom he had choſen, his Apoſtles, and had giuen them warrant, &amp; habilitie to teach,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19. The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred where the worde is preached.</note> whereby appeareth that the word preached and Sacraments muſt go together. Act. 10.47. Act. 16.32.33.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Where muſt it be miniſtred?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Where the worde is preached, and becauſe this Sacrament comprehendeth an holy and ſolemne introduction, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance into the Church of God,
<note place="margin">Priuate pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be not fit for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Mat. 28.19.</note> and is a teſtimonie of our heauenlie deliuerance, it is not lawfull to miniſter it, but in the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the faithful, as appeareth in that is ſaid, Go preach and baptize. &amp;c. and. Mar. 16.15.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrengthning of our faith, how many thinges do we principally learne by
<pb facs="tcp:21049:15"/>baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Eſpecially two, Firſt as water waſheth away the filthines of the fleſh: ſo the bloode of Chriſte doth waſh away ſin from my ſoule, as is written.
<note place="margin">Mar. 1.4.</note> Iohn did bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe in the wilderues, &amp; preach the baptiſm of amendment of life, for remiſſion of ſinns Secondly I am taught to riſe to newneſſe of life. For it is written, we are buried then with him by baptiſme into his death,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> that like as Chriſt was raiſed vp from the dead by the glory of his father, ſo we alſo ſhould walke in newneſſe of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein is the faith ſtrenthened in the vſe of the Lordes ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt as by the hande and mouthe my bodie receiueth bread and wine, ſo by faith, my ſoule feedeth of the body and blod of Chriſt. Ieſus ſaid vnto them,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.</note> I am that bread of lyfe, he that commeth to me ſhall not hunger, and he that beleeueth in mee ſhall neuer thirſte. Secondly, all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites of Chriſtes paſſion, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, are as ſurely ſealed to be mine, as I am ſure my body hath receiued the bread and wine, and as if I my ſelfe had wrought them. For it is written, He was
<pb facs="tcp:21049:16"/>deliuered to death for our ſinnes:
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> and is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen agayne for our iuſtification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Who ſhal be admitted to the Lords Supper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Chriſtian choyſe, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the Lords Supper.</note> Only they that can do thoſe things that are required of them that be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Children, fooles, madde folks, and the ignorant, muſt not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for they can not doe this.</note> What muſt they doe that be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers thereof?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Examine them ſelues: as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Muſt euery one that receiueth the Lordes Supper, of neceſſitie examine him ſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.</note> Hee muſt of neceſſitie, or elſe hee ſhall bee guilty of a moſte horrible ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu,</hi> Of what ſinne ſhall he bee guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vnworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers equall with the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Chriſt. 1. Cor. 11.27</note> Of the death of Chriſte, and ſhall be equall with thoſe murtherers that ſlew him: for it is written, Who ſoeuer ſhall eat this breade, and drinke the cup of the Lorde vnworthilie ſhall bee guilty of the bodie and bloode of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the rewarde of that ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Gods ſtanding vengeance &amp; eternall
<pb facs="tcp:21049:16"/>death, for it is written, he that eateth and drinketh vnwortily,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> eareth and drinketh his owne damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Seing the neceſſitie of this exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is ſo great, as may appeare by the iudgements of God, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> want of it,
<note place="margin">Ignorant mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe people shift ſinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvvixt them.</note> which yet is greatly to bee feared that very fewe do rightly conſider of. How many thinges muſte they eſpecially ſeeke for in them ſelues that do communicate?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Three.
<note place="margin">Three things to be eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered in examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Namely their eſtate before God: their right knowledge concerning the Sacrament: and their eſtate towards their brethren, or before the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> In ſeeking their eſtate before God what muſt they doe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt ſeeke their eſtate by nature according to the lawe rightly vnderſtoode, where they ſhall finde themſelues in the wrath of God, as S. Paule teſtifieth to the Epheſians, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.</note> We were by nature the children of wrath as well as others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Whereto ſerueth this, in ſearching their eſtate before God?
<note place="margin">In all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vve muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſpecially ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for the glory of God.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt for the glory of God, whiche is not duly conſidered, where our condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is not knowen. For it is written,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:17"/>Who careth for the Phiſition that is not ſicke.
<note place="margin">VVe muſt not shrinke to looke into our ſinnes, ſeeme they neuer ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, ſith the ſight of them ſerueth to shew vnto vs more plainly, the greatneſſe of the loue of God towards vs, in Chriſte.</note> Secondly, for their owne greater comfort, for the more they ſee their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation by nature, ſo muche more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth the loue of God to haue abounded towardes them in their deliueraunce by grace in Chriſt. As it is written, So God loued the world that he gaue his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Then as you would haue the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God to looke diligently into their naturall condemnation that is by the law, which adiudgeth euery one guyltie of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death that continueth not in ſuch abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and pure obedience as the lawe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, ſo you would not that they ſhoulde ſtaye there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">VVe beholde our ſinnes but the better to ſee the grace of Chriſt.</note> No in no caſe for then were there no hope of deliuerance, for vntil we atteine to him that hath conquered the lawe, the law ſtill reigneth ouer vs vnto death, as it is written, whatſoeuer the lawe ſaith, it ſaith it to them that are vnder the law. &amp;c. which no Chriſtian is, for Chriſt is not vnder the lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein ſtandeth the deliuerance of Gods choſen from his condemnation,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:17"/>that is by the lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Not in the works of the Lawe, nor in any childe of man, but onely in the free grace of God through Ieſus Chriſte, as it is written.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.25.</note> Oh wretched man that I am who ſhall deliuer mee from this body of death. I thank God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the meane of our attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to this righteouſnes of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Faith in him: as it is written, This is the will of him that ſent me,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.40.</note> that whoſoeuer ſeeth the ſonne and beleeueth in him, hath euerlaſting life, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> I remember you ſaid, that this faith was the peculier worke of the ſpirite of Chriſt, and his ordinarie meane to be only the preaching of the Goſpell, but I pray you wherevpon muſt this fayth be ſtayde or grounded? for a houſe without a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation will not long continue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Vpon the free promiſes of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">A conſcience feared with the ſighte of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes for ſinne, muſte not deal with the conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall promiſes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Why ſay you, free promiſes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe in the goſpel are promiſes with condition of our doing, or perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming which appertaine to the Lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the triall whether we haue
<pb facs="tcp:21049:18"/>this faith or no? for as it is eaſy to ſay that we haue it, ſo are there verie fewe or none that do not ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> We muſt by the effects learne to knowe the cauſe whiche woorketh them.
<note place="margin">The tree is knowen by his fruites.</note> This iuſtifiyng faith is a peculier worke of the Spirite of Chriſte, who lurketh no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but reneweth the heart, as Chriſte teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Nichodemus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.3.</note> ſaying. Except a man be borne againe, he can not ſee the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
            <p>He worketh in vs firſt,
<note place="margin">He doth not rightly hate others ſinnes, that loues his owne. Rom. 7.23.</note> an hatred and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of ſinne in all men, but eſpecially in our ſelues. As it is written. I ſee an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther law in my members rebelling againſt the lawe of my minde &amp;c. Secondly it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs to haue our whole delight and ioye
<note place="margin">The Lordes vvayes are grieuous to our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Rom. 5.1, 2.</note> in thoſe thinges which be agreeable to the will of God, as it is written, being iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by faith, we haue peace with God tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, by whome alſo we haue acceſſe into this grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſtande, and reioice vnder the hope of the glorie of God. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it frameth our liues in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the word: as, There is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them which are in Chriſte Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:21049:18"/>which walke not after the fleſhe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> but after the ſpirite.</p>
            <p>And fourthly it worketh effectually in
<note place="margin">Their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations are vayne, vvho holde their hope in hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>germugger, and profeſſe it not in the ſight of men. Ioh. 15.5.</note> vs that we expreſſe the ſame in our liues and conuerſations: as it is written. I am the vine and ye the vranches, he that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth muche fruite &amp;c. Mat. 7.18. Iames. 2.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Now concerning the ſeconde parte of this examination whiche apperteineth the ſupper it ſelfe: I pray you what is the Lordes ſupper?.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Lordes Supper vvhat it is.</note> It is a ceremonie inſtituted by Chriſt to confirme and manifeſt our ſociety and communion in his body and blood, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he come to indgement, as appeareth. He tooke bread, and when he had giuen thankes, he brake it and gaue to them ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This is my body whiche is giuen for you, doe this in remembrance of me.
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26, 27, 28.</note> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo he tooke the cup, ſaying. This cup is the new teſtament in my bloude which is ſhed for you. &amp;c. Mar. 14.27.</p>
            <p>And as oft as thou ſhalt eate this bread and drinke of this cup thou ſhall ſhewe the Lords death till he come.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Howe many thinges are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The author, the water, and the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Who is the authour of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The Lorde Ieſus Chriſt him ſelf, as appeareth Mat. 26.26. Mat 14.27. Luk. 22. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What thinges are wee taughte by that knowledge, namely that Chriſt is the author of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By the maieſty and wiſoome of the author is ſignified vnto vs, the excellencie and neceſſity of the thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Where muſt it be miniſtred?.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In the aſſembly of the faithfull, where the word is preached, for it is a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like action or deamed for the Churche as may appeare.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.17.18.20.</note> Now in this that I declare, I praye you not, that you come together not with profite but with hurt. Alſo when you come together into one place. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> How manie perſons are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in this action?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Two. The paſtor, and the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is to bee conſidered of both?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In the paſtor or miniſter, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not onely that he be able, but that he do preach the worde of the Lorde before vnto the people,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.24.</note> for Chriſt firſt preached to them of his death, and the indgement of God vpon the wicked. &amp;c. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles alſo did the like, as appeareth <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. and <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. Alſo in the people, that they examine them ſelues. For when Chriſt ſpake vnto them of the wicked fact of Iudas, euery one entred into his ſelfe, and ſayd, Maſter is it I?
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is needefull for euery one that is willing to receyue the Sacrament aright, to conſider of?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> When in examining him ſelfe, he come to conſider of the thing, and ſo to deale with the worde of the Lorde, he is eſpeciall to beware of wrong meaning,
<note place="margin">VVrong ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the vvorde is cauſe of much miſchiefe.</note> and falſe gloſes of the worde, wherein as we ſhall ſo eſcape two daungerous extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities about this Sacrament, ſo are we well warned by a ſorowfull experience of Adam, as may appeare <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Whiche are the two extremities that may by this herdefull auoyding of
<pb facs="tcp:21049:20"/>falſe and wrong meaning of the worde be eſcaped?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Tranſubſtantiation of the Papiſts, and ſuche like: and the vile contempt that Epicures, Atheiſtes, carnall Goſpellers, and many ignoraunt, do to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> In many places to this day (for want of the Lords good meanes to make the worde familiar to them, and to bring the people in obedience to be inſtructed in the wayes of the Lorde) you ſhall heare many ſay,
<note place="margin">Thoſe that feare the Lord ſee the trueth of this to their greefe.</note> that they looke to receiue Chriſt by the act of receiuing the outward ſignes: and ſome be yet ſo ignoraunt, that if you aſke them what they thinke ſo to receiue, they will anſwere, Their maker. I praye you what thinke you of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> Firſt you know it is written, that who ſo hath not the ſpirite of Chriſt, is none of his. So that he that bringeth not Chriſt, or rather is not brought of Chriſt to the Sacrament, may rather aſſure him ſelfe of the diuell and damnation, then to apply Chriſt and his merites to him, by the acte without faith,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.47, 48.</note> as maye well be ſeene in Iudas. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſay you to the ſtate of ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:21049:20"/>poore ſoules, as firſt be ignoraunt of all theſe: ſecondly, haue no ordinatie meane of further knowledge: and thirdly, be ſtraightly tyed vpon much bodily perill to receiue it by a day. And what holde you beſt for them to do?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt, if the Lorde haue ſet their aboade where his countenaunce, which is comfortably ſhewed by the Goſpell prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and Sacramentes rightly miuiſtred, is not to be leene, wherein alone ſtandeth their knowledge and fayth, they are to ſecke to the Arke, where it is,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.11.</note> euen to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Edoms houſe, and to heare what the Lorde ſayth to them, all excuſes ſet apart,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8.</note> Seeke ye my face. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the reſt, it is good not to runne into the daunger threatned of the Lord, nor to touch the way that leadeth to ſo great perill, before they ſhall haue learned the Lords trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Whereas you ſayde that this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament muſt be miniſtred where the word is preached, and ſhewed cauſe why. I pray you, what if ſome one that lyeth at the poynt of death, ſhould deſire that the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould come to deliuer him this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and hath there one or two of his
<pb facs="tcp:21049:21"/>neighbours or others that will receyue it with him for companie, becauſe there muſt be moe then one, yet that the Papiſtes thinke will ſerue, do you not thinke it good that he haue it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> What I thinke it matereth not much, except my thoughtes be ſtayed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the worde of God rightly vnderſtood.
<note place="margin">The beſte thoughts of the heart of man are vaine if they vvant the vvarrant of Gods vvorde. Prou. 2.1.</note> For all the thoughtes of the heart of man are vayne, and will caſily vaniſhe as the winde, except they be ſtrengthned by the Lords truth, which ſithe it alone muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs in all our actions, muche more in theſe of ſo great importance. For it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, My ſonne, if thou wilt receiue my wordes, and hide my commaundementes within thee, &amp;c. Then ſhalt thou vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande righteouſnes,
<note place="margin">Pro. 2.9.</note> iudgement, equitie, and euerie good path. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. but as for the matter of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande it ſhoulde ſeeme that whoſoeuer in ſuch ſorte deſireth the Sacrament, dothe neither rightly conſider him ſelfe the thing he deſireth, nor the ende why it was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and therefore needeth more inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and information of the Lorde, then the thing it ſelfe. And thus to miniſter the
<pb facs="tcp:21049:21"/>Sacrament, cauſeth many times the poore ſicke partie to put his hope and confidence in the externall fact and receyuing of the Sacrament, and neuer to thinke him ſelfe ſufficiently prepared to death, but when he hath receiued the externall ſigne. Alſo no parte of the Paſcall Lambe was brought to the ſicke, in the eating whereof, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating of the Paſſecuer was onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded the Lordes ordinance, wherevnto was nothing added or lefte out, and it was not done of any in prinate, but when the people did it together. As it is written,
<note place="margin">Exod. 2.6.</note> All the multitude of the congregation ſhall keepe it at euen, &amp;c. <hi>Num.</hi> 9.4.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> I pray you what is the cauſe, why you woulde the ſacraments not onely to be miniſtred where the word is preached, but when the word is preached.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt that we may holde proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Lordes people in celebrating the the Paſſeouer,
<note place="margin">Exod. 12.6. Num. 9.5, 4.</note> who held them ſelues ſtrait ly to al that which they had receiued of the Lorde. Alſo to glorifie the Lorde in yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding obedience to his worde. Who ſaid go preach and baptiſe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19. Mat. 26.20.</note> and in the inſtitution of this ſacrament he him ſelfe did the like
<pb facs="tcp:21049:22"/>Mark. 14.18. Luke 22.14. Iohn. 13.21. Alſo the ſacramentes are to the church of Chriſte, as ſeales of his promiſe, and what profiteth a ſeale without it be annexed to a grant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Doe you not thinke it ſuffiſeth in this behalfe if the worde be preached halfe a yeare or more, or leſſe before, and not at the ſame time, for whereas you ſpake of the ſeale to be onely in his vſe, when it is ioyned to the promiſe, you know that men make grantes, and ſeale them afterwards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Your reaſon of the vſages of men which make graunts and ſeale them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, if it proue any thing it ſhould ſeeme to proue this, that the promiſe may better be for a time without the ſeal, then the ſeal without the promiſe, yet you knowe that no man will ſeale a grant, but at the time of ſealing, he will heare the grant, and the meaning of euerie particular made plaine to all that haue intereſt or right in that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Alſo the Apoſtles who ſhoulde be our beſt preſident in this caſe, next to the Lord himſelfe, helde them ſelues ſtraightlie to that which they had receiued of the Lord, and haue not ſundred thoſe thinges which
<pb facs="tcp:21049:22"/>the Lord hath ioined together, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.
<note place="margin">Act. 20.7.</note> The diſciples being gathered together to breake bread, Paul preached vnto them. &amp;c. Acts. 2.41. Acts. 8.12. Acts. 9.17.18. Act. 10.34. Act. 16.15.32.33.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What inconuenience ſuppoſe you, may follow of the Sacramentes miniſtred without the worde preached?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Contempt of the Lorde, and an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of iuſtifying in the act, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with papiſts, and vnbeleeuers, and for the moſte parte thoſe that be ignorant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> The papiſts ſay that in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords ſupper, after the words (of confirmation as they call them) be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, there remaineth no more bread but the verie bodie of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">A perillous proofe of wrong mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the vvorde.</note> reallie and naturallie and they ſay they haue the worde to proue it, namelie, the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt to his diſciples ſaying. This is my body. What thinke you of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The Papiſtes and vnbeleeuers in ſaying that theſe words of our Sauiour are of power to chaunge the nature of the bread, &amp; in the very pronunciation to make the body of Chriſt, forget them ſelues, and in the enteraunce of their cauſe commit a
<pb facs="tcp:21049:23"/>foule ouerſight. For Chriſt in ſaying, this is my body, proueth it to be his body in ſuche ſort as he ment it before the wordes be ſpoken, and ſayth not that after the words ſpoken it ſhould be his body, which they muſt confeſſe, or els they wil be found to miſname the thing, and call bread fleſhe, whiche I thinke they will not laye vnto Chriſtes charge, who ſaid, it is my body, not, it ſhall be my body, or is made my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by the words that I ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> In deede as you ſay, the words do playnly import that it is his body before in ſuch ſort as he ment it (in whoſe mouth is no guile) This is my body. Eut I pray you, may this their falſe iugling be made to appeare by the worde, in any ſuche ſorte as their nakedneſſe may be ſeene to the ſimple. For as ſtrumpets and brothels oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times pretende great ſhewe of honeſtie, ſo doe the Papiſtes and their friendes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende great matter for the mainteinaunce of this, and ſet a notable face on it, and I perceiue that ſith they meane ſtill to dwell in the dregges of Romiſh idolatrie, it doth muche ſtande them vpon to lye apace for the holding vp of this curſed vntruth. For
<pb facs="tcp:21049:23"/>it is the chiefeſt prop of all the reſt, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with that, &amp; downe goes their prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, who, (they ſay) haue greate ſkill and ſinguler dexteritie to make the Lords body when they lifte?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> There be ſufficient proofes in the worde (the beſt witneſſe) to all them that haue not hardned their hearts and faces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, as appeareth that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes haue, for it may be truely auouched of them that is written, The deafe adder ſtoppeth her eare, and will not heare the voyce of the charmer, charme he neuer ſo wiſely. And albeit I haue ſmall hope to profite them to amendement, yet for their ſakes that may be ſnared with their ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to helpe them to one witnes more of the Lords vndoubted trueth to their dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per iudgement, I will here ſet downe a fewe, wherein I truſt their falſehood ſhall ſomewhat be ſeene to all that are not blind of purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilitie.</note> the tranſubſtantiation which they ſo ſtraine after, teacheth an impoſſible thing, namely the breaking of the body of Chriſt, for they ſay it is the very naturall body, and the worde addeth breaking vnto
<pb facs="tcp:21049:24"/>it. So that if it be (as they ſeme not vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſay) the very naturall body of Chriſt, then is Chriſtes body and bones broken in the celebration of the Supper, ſo that he is worſe vſed amongſt his deareſt friends, then he was at the handes of his greateſt enimies. For the Scripture witneſſeth that they brake not a bone of him.
<note place="margin">Io 19.33, 36</note> Alſo this breaking that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, doth proue it to be bread after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words ſpoken, for breaking hath reſpect to a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for no accident can be broken: but there we ſee the accidents of the bread, as the ſhewe and taſte, and the Apoſtle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth breaking. Therefore it muſt needes be the ſame after that it was before, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ouerthroweth the trueth of Chriſtes body, for to ſay that the bread is become the very naturall body of Chriſte that was borne of the virgin, is to ſay that he is in the fleſhe in many places at once, and it mainteineth the error of Martion,
<note place="margin">It proueth Chriſtes body to be phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticali.</note> which ſayd that Chriſt had but a phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical body: and alſo the error of Entiches, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two natures in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it deſtroyeth our fayth, as may
<pb facs="tcp:21049:24"/>appeare by that definition of fayth giuen by the holy Ghoſt.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1. It deſtroyeth our fayth.</note> Faith is the ground of things that are hoped for and the euidence of things which are not ſeene. But if there be the naturall body of Chriſt vnder the forme of bread as they ſay, then it can not be denied but we ſee it, for they ſaye it is not bread that we ſee, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">The Papiſtes vnder a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> shew of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deliuer death.</note> therefore this teacheth that we can haue no fayth in this action, and if we do it not in fayth, all that we do therein is ſinne: as it is written, Whatſoeuer is not of fayth is ſinne.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">It is contrary to the vvorde of God.</note> it is contrary to the worde of God in other places, and giueth a priuate ſence to that place, which S. Peter ſayth the word of God can not beace, for he ſayth that there is no priuate interpretation in the worde. And it is reſtefied in the worde,
<note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> that the heauens muſt receiue him vntill the time of there ſtoring of all things. And Chriſt him ſelfe ſayth, If they ſhal ſay vnto you, Lo here is Chriſt, or there is Chriſt, beleeue them not.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,
<note place="margin">It is agaynſt the articles of our fayth.</note> it diſcenteth from the articles of our fayth, which ſay, He aſſended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſitteth on the right hande of God
<pb facs="tcp:21049:25"/>the father, from whence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <p>Sixtly it deſtroſeth the inſtitution of the Lordes ſupper,
<note place="margin">It denieth the continuance of the Lords Supper.</note> which was commanded to be continued and vſed vntill the Lord him ſelfe ſhould come. If nowe therefore, he be really preſent in the bodye of his fleſh, then muſt the ſupper ceaſe.</p>
            <p>And laſtlie,
<note place="margin">It is agaynſt the trueth of the vvorde of God. Mat. 26.20.</note> it ouerthroweth the trueth of Chriſtes wordes, for he bid them doe it in remembrance of him, now a remembrance and the thing remembred be not one, ſo that if Chriſt be really and corporally preſent in the Sacrament, the remembraunce is cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for the thing remembrance preſenteth it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Alſo if the wordes and the thing mente by the wordes be one, then is the cup and not the wine in the cup the teſtamente in Chriſts bloud,
<note place="margin">Luc. 22.20.</note> for it is written. This cup is the newe teſtament in my bloud, which is ſhed for you. Iohn. <hi>13.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo if the bread be turned into the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Thus they iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</note> then the wicked eat his fleſh and drinke his bloud, but the wicked doe not eat the fleſh of Chriſt or drinke his bloude, therefore it is not tranſubſtantiate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Why the wicked do eat the fleſhe of Chriſte, do they not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No, for then ſhould they haue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, as it is written,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.54.</note> Who ſo eateth my fleſh &amp; drinketh my blood, hath euerlaſting life, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is bread after the wordes be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Now proue you that?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The Apoſtle calleth it breade both before and after,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.27.</note> and therefore not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall bodie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> They will ſay he calleth it breade after becauſe it was before, as Symon the leaper and Naaman were called leapers when they were clenſed, becauſe they had bene leprouſe,
<note place="margin">Exod. 7.12,</note> And Moſes his rodde being turned into a ſerpent was called ſtil a rod.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In theſe was a plaine ſhewe to the ſenſes that they were changed, but in this it is not ſo, but eſpeciallie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle puttes it oute of doubt, adding breaking to it, whiche can not agree with the bodie of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Alſo if the breade and wine be tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiate, and tourned into the body and blood of Chriſte, then was it tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate
<pb facs="tcp:21049:26"/>at his laſt ſupper, but it was not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation at his laſt ſupper, therefore there is no ſuch change of the breade and wine as they immagine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Why was it not tranſubſtantiate at his laſt ſupper?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No, for then ſhoulde Chriſtes natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body which ſate at the table, haue bene alſo at one inſtant in their mouthes, ſo that it muſt needes haue followed that he either had two bodies or elſe that his bodie was phantaſticall, and not a true bodie, whiche can be but in one place at ouce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But they will ſay that a glorified bodie may be euerie where, and therefore both at the table and in their mouthes at one inſtant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Beſides that to ſay that Chriſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified bodye may bee euery where, is to ſpeake an intollerable vntrueth, for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt ſaith, concerning his body which he tooke of the virgin, he aſſended into heauen, &amp; ſitteth on the right hand of God and from thence ſhall he come &amp;c. ſo, if his bodie was not glorified till he roſe againe (which I truſt they will grant) then was it not glorified at his laſt ſupper, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb facs="tcp:21049:26"/>not at the table &amp; in their mouths by their owne reaſon.</p>
            <p>Alſo Chriſt is teſtified to be like his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in all thinges,
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.17.</note> whereby we are put in ſome experience (in that his body was like ours, in all thinges except ſinne, and our bodies will not bee forced into ſuche a ſtraight withall their coniuringes, as to be cloſed in a peece of bread) that Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is not changed in ſuch ſorte as they i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſay you to the miniſtring of the Lords Supper vnder one kind, and of keping the Lords cuppe from the people?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Chriſt did miniſter it in both,
<note place="margin">Once decline from the worde, and ther is no ſtay in falling.</note> whoſe inſtitution it is not lawfull for any man to alter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Some ſay, that the Churche vpon good conſideration may alter what they will, and as they ſee cauſe, in Rites, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montes, and Sacramentes.
<note place="margin">Chriſtes Church is his ſpouſe, and is obedient to the vvorde, but the church of Rome is a ſtrumpet, and will rule the vvorde.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The Inſtitution of this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtandeth vpon the order, example, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of Chriſt: for firſt be deuided the bread ſeuerally from the cup, and the cup ſeuerally from the bread. Secondly, in this he gaue vs example to doe the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:21049:27"/>vnto the ende of the worlde. Thirdly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this order taken and example left, he added alſo an expreſſe commaundement, ſaying, Do this, drinke ye all of this. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt this order, example, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Goſpell, no Churche nor counſell of man or Angell hath any power or authoritie to chaunge or alter, for it is written,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8, 9.</note> If any bring vnto you any other doctrine beſides that which you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, holde him accurſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> They ſay further, why may not the Church as well alter the forme of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, as the Apoſtles did the forme of Baptiſme, where S. Peter ſayth, Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one be baptized in the name of Ieſus Chriſte.
<note place="margin">Acts. 2.38.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That Scripture, nor any other, proueth that the Apoſtles vſed this forme of baptiſing, I baptiſe thee in the name of Chriſt: but they vſed many times this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeache, to be baptiſed in the name of Chriſt, not as expreſſing thereby the formable words of baptiſing, but as mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that they would haue them to become members of Chriſt, and to be baptiſed as Chriſtians, entring into his baptiſme, and
<pb facs="tcp:21049:27"/>not onely into the baptiſme of Iohn: and therfore although the Apoſtles thus ſpake, yet notwithſtanding when they baptiſed any them ſelues, they vſed doubtleſſe the forme preſcribed of Chriſt, and none other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What doe the faythfull receiue in the Lordes Supper then, more then onely bread and wine?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> For our reſolution in this,
<note place="margin">Contemners of the Lordes miſteries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane his trueth.</note> we muſt haue reſpect vnto the minde of Chriſte, which is beſt knowen by his words, who ſayth, This is my body. Which words of Chriſt be moſt true: and leaſt we ſhould be like vnto ſtrumpets, which onely looke to the gyſtes, and neuer regarde the minde of the giuer, in a certayne aſſuraunce of the vndoubted truth of the words of the Lord, I couclude that as to the outwarde ſenſes it is bread and wine, ſo to the ſoule, beeing receiued in fayth, it is the body and bloud of Chriſt. Baptiſme is not onely a ſigne of waſhing away of our ſinnes, but is, in a ſpirituall maner, a very waſhing and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from ſinne. Ananias ſayde to Paule, Ariſe and waſhe away thy ſinnes.
<note place="margin">Acts. 22.16.</note> So the ſupper is called a pertaking of the Lords body, and not a ſigne of the pertaking of
<pb facs="tcp:21049:28"/>the Lords body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Sithe the body of Chriſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the worde doth witneſſe, and we in the earth as experience doth proue, howe can we communicate with his body and bloud?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reaſon is a beaſt in Gods cauſes.</note> In deede to our carnall reaſon it is an abſurde thing, and therefore the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes &amp; vnbeleeuers meaſuring the Lords wayes by their corruption, on the one ſide haue blindly imagined their tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and the Epicures and ſuch like, in the like meaſure thinke of the Lordes my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries prophanely, as namely in this, that in the Lords Supper is onely bare bread and wine. Contrary to both which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that ſupernaturally and ſpiritually by faith holding faſt the truth of the Lords promiſe, we communicate with, and are made pertakers of the body and bloud of Chriſt. And albeit in deede the body of Chriſt is ſo farre from our eies and ſenſes, and therefore from the place where we ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Supper concerning his bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſence, as heauen is from the earth: in ſo muche as this action is heauenly, and our fayth aſcendeth thither, that it maye
<pb facs="tcp:21049:28"/>moſt effectuall apprehende Chriſt, in this reſpect whoſoeuer doth not graunt that the fleſhe of Chriſt is moſt effectually preſent in the Supper, maketh boyde the Supper of the Lorde, for Chriſt ſayth, This is my body which is giuen for you,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26.</note> This is my bloud which is ſhed for you. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. which words can not be reſtrayned to the effects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> There be that thinke that whereas Chriſt then ſpeaketh of his bodie he, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not his natural bodie, but his miſtical body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> There can be nothing more abſurde there &amp; fooliſh then that, for we our ſelues are the miſticall body, whereof Chriſte is the head, and therfore nothing can be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more without ſence, then that we ſhold be commaunded to eate the miſticall body of Chriſt which was giuen for vs, that is, that we ſhould eat our ſelues giuen for our ſelues. Alſo what ſhall be ſaide when wee come to ſpeake of the blood, for the Church is not called the miſticall blood of Chriſt. That blinde imagination, therefore euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not the eating of the very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:21049:29"/>and drinking of the very bloud of Chriſt which you ſpeake of, proue his bodie to be phantaſticall (that is, not a true bodie in deede, but a bodie by immagination) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that many doe eat it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In eating the body of Chriſte, wee muſt diſtinguiſh betweene the ſpirituall eating which the Church of God vſeth in fayth, and the carnall eating whiche they that holde tranſubſtantiation and conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation do imagine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Chriſt ſaith. The wordes that I ſpeake are ſpirit and life, the fleſh profiteth nothing, it is the ſpirit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quickeneth. How ſay you then, that we muſt eat the very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt and drinke his bloode?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The fleſhe of Chriſte profiteth not beeing eaten carnally or with the mouth, which kinde of eating the Capernites did, and the Papiſtes doe fancie, who, becauſe they behelde nothing in Chriſte more then in other men, they were to be admoniſhed, that the fleſh of Chriſte was, and is to be eaten ſpiritually by fayth, and not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with the teeth.</p>
            <p>And further, the worde, eating, is not properly but by tranſlation, and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:21049:29"/>of ſpeech,
<note place="margin">VVhat's me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by this worde eat, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and vſe of the Lords ſupper.</note> applied to the ſpiritual recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and by a ſacramentall kind of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, whereby that which is proper to the ſignes is tranſferred to the thing ſignified. Therefore when we ſpeake of ſpirituall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, we are to vnderſtand that this worde eating, ſignifieth nothing elſe, but by faith to apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or to ioyne it vnto our ſelues.</p>
            <p>There be two euilles about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment carefully to be auoided, and we are alſo taught that wiſdom by the holy ghoſt. For leaſt we ſhoulde with the Papiſtes thinke Chriſts body preſent,
<note place="margin">Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration &amp;c. and contempt</note> in or with the breade really, naturally, carnally to be receiued with our bodely mothes (where there is no other preſence of Chriſtes body then ſpirituallie, &amp; to faith in many places he keepeth ſtil the name of bread. And leaſt we ſhold make to light of it,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 1. Cor. 11.</note> accounpting it but a bare ſigne and no better then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon breade. The holy Ghoſte calleth it Chrſtes body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Then you ſeeme to deſire y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the Lord, ſhoulde be vſed with al due reuerence do, you not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In any wiſe and ſuch as feare and loue the Lord, will (I am ſure) willinglie
<pb facs="tcp:21049:30"/>condiſcend thereto. And to that end I wiſh that the Sacrament of the Lordes ſupper ſhoulde be eſteemed and called of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans after Chriſtes words, as diuers of the fathers eſteemed the Sacramentes after Chriſtes words, and not after the outward appearaunce, as in the ſupper the breade Chriſtes bodie, and the wine Chriſts blood rather then other waies. Not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I thereby meane any other preſence of Chriſts body then a preſence of grace, a preſence to faith a preſence ſpiritually, not carnally, really, and naturally as the papiſts do meane, for in ſuch ſorte Chriſtes body is onely in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whither our faith aſcendeth, in the vſe of the Sacramente and receiueth whole Chriſte accordinglie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Yea, but to call the Sacramente on that ſort, is to giue occaſion of Idolatrie to the people, whiche will take the outwarde ſignes which they ſee, ſimply for Chriſtes body, as we haue too muche experience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Therefore I take it, it were better and leſſe daungerous to call it bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In deede great idolatrie is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in and about this Sacrament, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men ought to be as beedefull as they
<pb facs="tcp:21049:30"/>can to auoyde occaſioning it, or doing any thing that may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme it. But in as much as the holy Ghoſt is wiſer then men, and did foreſee the euils that might be, and yet notwithſtanding doth cal it Chriſtes body, I thinke we ſhould do euill to take vpon vs to reforme his ſpeach.
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26.</note> If miniſters did their duties in catechiſing and preaching, then doubtles, to cal the Sacrament Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body, and to eſteeme it accordingly, could not giue occaſion to Idolatry. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, wo to them that preach not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But to call the Sacrament Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body, &amp; to make none other preſence then by grace, or ſpiritually to faith (which is of things hoped for, and which appeare not to the bodily ſenſes) is to make no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at all, or to make him none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes preſent then he is in his word when it is preached, and therefore what neede we to receiue the Sacrament, ſeeing that by the doctrine a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may receiue him day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the fieldes as well, and as muche, as in the Church in the vſe of the ſacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In deede neither the Scripture, nor chriſtian fayth will giue vs leaue to make or alowe any carnall, naturall, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:31"/>or any ſuch groſſe preſence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body, for it is in heauen, and as the ſcripture doth witneſſe, the heauens muſt haue it till his comming to iudgement, Except we would deny the humanitie of Chriſt, and the trueth of mans nature in hun. The preſence therefore which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue &amp; confeſſe, is ſuch a preſence as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon knoweth not, and the worlde can not learne, nor any that looketh in this matter with our naturall eyes,
<note place="margin">The worlde knovveth not the Lordes vvaies.</note> or heareth with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eares then with the eares, and ſeeth with the eyes of fayth. Whiche fayth, though it be of things hoped for, and ſo of things abſent to the corporall ſenſes, yet this abſence is not an abſence in deede, but to reaſon and the olde man, the nature of fayth beeing a poſſeſſion of things hoped for, as appeareth <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. Therefore to grauut a preſence to fayth, is not to make no preſence at all, but to ſuche as know no righte chriſtian fayth. Alſo the ſame meate is offered in the words of the Scripture, which is offered in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that no leſſe is Chriſtes body of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by the Scriptures then by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, but hereof may no man gather,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:31"/>that therefore it needeth not to receiue the Sacrament, or to affirme that a man may as much by him ſelfe, meditating the mord in the field, receiue Chriſtes body, as in the church in the right vſe of the Sacrament. For Chriſt ordeined nothing in vayne or ſuperfluouſly, and he ſayth, Take and eate this, and he ordeineth nothing whereof we haue not neede. Agayne,
<note place="margin">The Lordes vvaies be righteous.</note> though in the fields a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may receiue Chriſles body, by faith in the meditation of the worde, yet I deny that a man doth ordinarilic receiue Chriſtes bodie by the onelie meditation of his death or hearing of his worde, with ſo much ſight, &amp; by ſuch ſenſes be aſſurance, (whereof our infirmitie hath great need) as by the receiuing of the ſacrament, not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt is not ſo much preſent in his worde preached, as hee is in or with his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but becauſe there bee mo windows open for Chriſt to enter into vs, in the par ticipation of the Sacrament, then by his worde preached or hearde. For in the word Chriſt entereth into our hearts only by the eares, and through hearing, but in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is ſealed the promiſes of God in the experience of all our ſences.
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Then you ſay that the Sacrament rightlie receiued is Chriſtes bodie and bloud, do you not:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yea, I ſay yet further, that it is Chriſtes bodie broken, which ioyned with eating doth ſet another difference betwene vs and the papiſts, for that we affirme that it is not the bodie of Chriſte, before it be eate of the faithfull,
<note place="margin">Eating goeth before the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie that it is his body.</note> for Chriſt ſaide, take eat, this is my bodie, ſo that eating doth go before, which if they had knowne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, it would eaſily haue put an end to all their vile and vaine queſtions aboute their hoſte (as they call it) rotting in the pix, and of a mouſe or ſuch like eating it. Alſo the breaking of the bodie of Chriſte &amp; ſhedding of his bloude which the ſcripture witneſſeth, giueth vs to ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof, and the exceeding horror of Gods iuſt wrath againſte our ſinnes,
<note place="margin">The horror of Gods wrath for ſinne is much more then the moſt can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of.</note> which could neuer be pacified, or cur ſinnes done away, but by this meanes, namely, by the breaking of the bodie and ſhebding of the bloude of our Lorde and alone ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What benefites haue we by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the communion?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt by worthy receiuing this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, we abide in Chriſt, and Chriſte in vs.</p>
            <p>Alſo we atteine an heauenly and celeſtial life, in aſſurance to be cuer with the Lorde in the lande of the liuing, for it is written he that eateth my fleſhe,
<note place="margin">Ion. 6.41.</note> and drinketh my blood hath cuerlaſting life, and I wil raiſe him vp at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>And alſo we receiuing the Lorde Ieſus Chriſte by faith with all the benefites of his death, wee receiue in a certeine aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the remiſſion of our ſinnes and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thus be thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the blinde multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude perſvva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, vvhiche dreame to them ſelues they shall be vvell, though they neuer haue more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion then a horſe.</note> Is it not ſufficient to holde that we are made partakers of Chriſtes benefites though we haue in the mean time no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion or fellowſhippe with the body of Chriſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That is no leſſe abſurde, then if I ſhoulde ſay, that one liueth by that meate which he did neuer eate, or recouer health by that medicine which he did neuer taſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Now concerning the thirde matter aboute the Sacramente, in examination which (as you ſaid) was the end for which it was ordeined of the Lorde, and ſo to bee
<pb facs="tcp:21049:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>receiued of vs, I pray you wherefore was it ordeined, and to what end ſhall a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The end is Gods glory, &amp; the profite of his Church.</note> To preuide for his owne glorie, and the profite of his Church, remedying two great and continuall euils in vs, namely forgetfulneſſe of Gods benefites, &amp; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of Gods fauoure towardes vs, and alſo to ſhewe forth our profeſſion before the Church, and and in the face of the enimie.</p>
            <p>Firſt that we might be holden in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall mindfulneſſe of Gods benefites.
<note place="margin">The Lordes ſupper doth put vs in minde of the death of Ghriſt.</note> The cheefe and principall of all other is heare preſented to vs, namely the death of Chriſt the alone, and deare ſonne of God, and to this end Chriſte ſaith. Doe this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me.</p>
            <p>And to aſſure vs of the vnfaigned loue of God towards vs, what can be more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall then to be in the fellowſhip of bys owne ſonne, in whom the loue that he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth towards vs is without ende or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<note place="margin">I. Cor. 11.25. It doth aſſure vs of his loue.</note> for his mercy endureth for euer, and of this loue of God towards vs, we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Sacrament: as it is written, The bread which we breake is it not the communion of the body of Chriſte? Is not
<pb facs="tcp:21049:33"/>the cuppe of bleſſing which we bleſſe, the partaking of the bloud of Chriſt? So as we are ſet in mindfulneſſe of that which we ſhould neuer forget, ſo alſo are we put in aſſuraunce of that whereof we maye not doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> The Papiſts ſay that a man ought not to be ſure of his ſaluation by Chriſte,
<note place="margin">A doctrine fit for papiſtes, but not for the Lords people.</note> howe thinke you of it:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No maruel though they teach men to doubt alwayes of their ſaluation, the ground of whoſe teaching is their owne gayne. For once let the trueth take place, that Chriſtians be by the worde and ſpirite of Chriſt aſſured of their ſaluation by him,
<note place="margin">The Papiſtes God is his ovvne belly.</note> then downe goes their Prieſthood, their pardons, their trentals, their dirgies, their chaunteries, their ſencing, their ſinging, their Maſſes and prayers for the dead, with what ſoeuer of like ſort, for take away the gaine, and all theſe will quickly lye in the duſte. But we are wartanted by the word of the Lord, that the Lords children oughte to bee ſure of their ſaluation by Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.1.</note> In deede carnall men that meaſure all by reaſon, ſee not howe. But the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay ſayth,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 26.</note> With my body ſhall they
<pb facs="tcp:21049:34"/>riſe, and S. Paule ſayth, They ſhall haue reſt with vs.
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.</note> Alſo it is written, His ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite doth certifie our ſpirite that we are the ſonnes of God. Now if we be ſure that we are Gods ſonnes, we are alſo ſure of Gods grace and fauour, and ſo conſequently of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Is there no other ende of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yes. That he which worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth, ſhould be certayne of the remiſſion of al his ſinnes, how many or great loeuer they be, and ſo labour to aduaunce the prayſe of God for his mercy: but howe great this kindnes of the Lorde is,
<note place="margin">They beſte knowe vvhat ſinne is that feele the vveight of it.</note> they onely know who haue felt the burthen of ſinne, which of all woes in this life is the greateſt, and of all burthens the moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy. Agayne, no man can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with Chriſtes body &amp; bloud, but the ſame muſt communicate with his ſpirice,
<note place="margin">He that hath not the ſpirite of Chriſt is none of his, he that hath his ſpirite, hath proofe of his effects.</note> for Chriſtes body is no dead carkas. Nowe he that communicateth with Chriſtes ſpirite, is made partaker of Chriſtes righteouſnes, holynes, innocencie, and immortalitie, and of all the merites of Chriſt, and his whole glory. For it is written, The glory which
<pb facs="tcp:21049:34"/>thou gaueſt me, I haue giuen them. He alſo is made partaker with the Church, and all the good that euer it or any mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it, had, hath, or ſhall haue, for there is in it a communion and fellowſhippe of Saintes which we beleue, and which hath wayting on it alwayes the forgiuenes of ſinnes, the riſing agayne, and eternall lyfe with God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> In examining our ſelues,
<note place="margin">The third mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> what els muſt we looke for?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Our eſtate before the Churche,
<note place="margin">The ſtate of the faythfull before the Church.</note> wherein is required not onely that we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue from our hearts thoſe that haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended vs, that we may haue an experience within our ſelues of Chriſtes ſpirit, and ſo glorifie God in our heartes, by aſſurance of his mercy in forgiuing vs, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of vs in Chriſt. As it is written, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue, and you ſhall be forgiuen. <hi>Math.</hi> 6. But alſo we muſte ſeeke to be reconciled to them whom we haue offended. As it is written,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.23.</note> If thou offreſt thy gyft vpon the alter, and there remembreſt that thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ought agaynſt thee, leaue there thy gifte, and go and be reconciled firſt to thy brother, and then come and offer thy
<pb facs="tcp:21049:35"/>gifte, and this muſt not only be done of vs before we come to the Sacrament, but alſo concerning prayer to the Lorde. For it is written, When you pray ſay thus: Our father, &amp;c, Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe agaynſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But were it not better, firſte to doe theſe thinges that concerne Gods glory, &amp; then to ſeeke reconcilement afterwardes, for is not this to prefer to offices of charity before the worſhip of God, and to ſet the the ſecond table which cencerneth our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, before the firſt which concerneth the Lorde him ſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> As the heart of man is prone into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of offence euen from the wombe, and hath not any inclination of it ſelfe into the way of the Lord,
<note place="margin">The naturall man hath an cuill heart.</note> ſo they in vain pretend to haue receiued eternall bleſſings from him by his ſpirite, where there is not in ſome meaſure theſe &amp; the like fruites of the ſame ſpirite. And the Lorde taxeth them as falſe pretenders to worſhip God, which proudly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temn their brethren who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And vnder one kinde, he ſetteth downe the outward exerciſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine worſhip, wherby men ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times do more cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfet
<pb facs="tcp:21049:35"/>lines, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truly teſtify it, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of al hipocrits, as it is ſeen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pharaſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> The papiſtes in ſteede of all this ſay, goe to the prieſte and tell him all thy ſinnes, &amp; then come at Eaſter and receiue &amp;c. do you thinke it well?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No, nothing of vs ought to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted well done that is not done to the gloric of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Why they will ſay they doe it to the glorie of God, and how can you prooue the contrarie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi>
               <note place="margin">There is no good thing vvithout the light of the vvorde.</note> Nothing can be done to the gloric of God without obedience. There is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience without the worde, ſo that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, nothing can bee done to the glory of God without the teſtemony of the worde. But theſe vile immaginations be not only without the worde, which were enough to throw them withall their good put poſes &amp; intents down to the diuel in iudgment, but that they may holde their intereſt in a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and more horrible vengeance, they are directly agaynſt the manifect teſtimonies of the worde of the Lorde. Firſt they will haue the people to confeſſe their ſinnes to them. The Scripture willeth vs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21049:36"/>our ſinnes to the Lorde onely. Dauid ſayth, Remember not Lorde the ſinnes of my youth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.7. Pſa. 51.3, 4.</note> &amp;c. And agayne, Agaynſt thee O Lorde, haue I ſinned. Alſo Luke tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs by the example of the loſt ſonne, to confeſle our ſinnes to the Lorde. The Publicane ſayde,
<note place="margin">Luc. 15.1. Luc. 18.18.</note> Lorde be mercifull to me a ſinner. And where the Prieſtes ſay, they muſt confeſſe all, the Prophet Dauid ſayth, Who can tell howe ofte hee offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.12.</note> Alſo where as they ſay they can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Sooner ſayde then proued.</note> they ſhew their fuſt condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, namely that the diuell and ſinne reigneth in them. For if they can forgiue ſinnes, then Chriſt dyed in vayne. But let God be euerlaſtingly true, and the diuell and all Papiſtes lyers. I, euen I am he (ſayth the Lord) that put away thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities for mine owne ſake,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 43.23.</note> and will no more remember thy ſinnes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.8. Alſo whereas they alow the Sacrament to the people onely at Eaſter, they do in that as in the reſt, for as they robbe the Lorde of his honour, and put an holines in the time, ſo all the other times of the yere, wherein the Lorde ſayth to the whole Church (in reſpect of the Supper beeing a publike
<pb facs="tcp:21049:36"/>action) Take ye, ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ye: the Papiſts ſay, let the Prieſt eate it alone, and let all the people gaſe &amp; looke on. But be the Lords trueth neuer ſo playne ageynſt this kind of ſuperſtitious receyuing the Lords Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet ſuch force hath theſe deuiſes of the diuell to holde the vngodly in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that you ſhall ſee many in many places, and they not the leaſt, euen at this day,
<note place="margin">The Popes friends which profeſſe to ferue the Lord by ſeaſons, come once a yere to the Sacrament, more for feare of the lawe then for loue to the Lord.</note> who at Eaſter will come very deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and all the yere after neuer a whit, in whom the foule ſtenche of the diuels excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, in theſe and the like practiſes of popery, hath ſo foreſtalled their ſenſes, that there is no place in them for the ſweete fauour of the worde of lyfe, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ſleepeth not. And for ſo muche as theſe and their Popiſh teachers hold vp an other doctrine then Chriſt hath taught vs, we are warranted by the Apoſtle to holde them accurſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſay you to the place of Saint Iames which thy alleage for eare confeſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">Iames. 5.16.</note> where he ſaith confeſſe your ſinnes one to another?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Saint Iames in the wiſedome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holie Ghoſte prouideth for the comfort of
<pb facs="tcp:21049:37"/>Gods choſen in the diſtreſſe of ſpirite tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the conſcience of ſinne, in which caſe he adutſeth the Lords people to imparte them, ſuch greefe with ſome ſuch of their brethren, as in the wiſedome of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite according to the folowwip of his, hee may iuſtly hope both for ſuch counſell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warrantiſe of the word, as his ſoul needeth and alſo may be ſtrengthened by his fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent prayers to the Lord, and ſo the words following proue, for he ſaith Confeſſe your ſinnes one to another, and pray one for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that ye may be healed, &amp;c. Alſo if this gaue any ſtrength to eare confeſſion, then muſt the prieſte confeſſe him to one, which they wil not grant therfore they do, but ingle with the Lordes trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Then you will take nothing from any mans warrant,
<note place="margin">No warrant is faſe but the Loras.</note> namely the Papiſtes without proofe of the worde of God right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnderſteode.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No, for leauing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; their friendes, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their vnwritten verities. Ioh. 4.25.5, 39 16.13. Their chopping &amp; changing of the worde, Deut. 5.2.12.32. Their holding them miufficient to deeide controuerſies, Pſa. 19.7. Luk. 16.20. Therfore keeping
<pb facs="tcp:21049:37"/>them from the people. Pſal. 95.10. Iohn. 17.3. Their imagination of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures darkneſſe. Pſal. 19.7.
<note place="margin">Some of the dregges of the Popes Church</note> Their vayne boaſting of the Churches authoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the worde of God. <hi>Iero.</hi> 7.8. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Their falſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of works. <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.3 <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10. Their preſumptuous opinion of the Popes ſupremacie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.28.19. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.23. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.26. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. Their eare confeſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.7. Their Purgatorie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.3, 4. Their praying for the dead, their Maſſes, and trentals, and dirgies. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.26. Their praying to Samtes, <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. Their olde cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and following of forefathers. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.2, 3.12.30. Their Latin ſeruice. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6, 7, 8. Their Images. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4. Their tranſubſtantiation. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. Their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching prieſthood. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. The diuerſities of meates for conſcience ſake, and a thouſand mo abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4. We reſt our ſelues wholly &amp; ſafely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alone word of God, as vpon a moſt truſtie witneſſe of all trueth, that fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:21049:38"/>not: for it is written, Heauen and earth ſhall periſhe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.35.</note> but not one ſote of the worde of the Lorde ſhall fayle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> I woulde be moſte glad to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate with the Church of God in the vſe of this Saccament, ſo oft as they come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to that ende: but I ſee it is a thing moſt worthy ſuch reuerent conſideration, as is commanded vnto vs in the word, &amp; I ſee the horror of my ſinnes ſo great,
<note place="margin">The beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are ſooneſt feared vvith ſinne</note> &amp; fecle in my ſelfe ſo litle repentance and fayth, that I feare I am vnworthy to receiue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In deede to the worthy receiuing of the Lords ſupper, ſuche examination of euery one in his owne conſcience as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle requireth, is very needfull. But as for ſinne, which is in euery one by nature, which alſo of it ſelfe is deadly, euen from the greateſt to the leaſt, we are to diſcerne our eſtate in that caſe not by the ſinne, but by the partie, as we are taught in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rom. 6. where he willeth that ſinne do not reign in vs, which it doth in euery child of man till the ſpirite of Chriſt be giueu vnto vs by the preaching of the Goſpell. As it is written, A ſtrong man armed keeping the houſe, all that he poſſeſſeth be in peace, till
<pb facs="tcp:21049:38"/>a ſtronger then he come, &amp;c. Then our ſinnes bee deadely,
<note place="margin">VVho ſinne deadly.</note> when they haue the reigne and dominion in vs, And ſinne reigneth when we giue ouer to ſinne, when we ſtriue not agayuſt it,
<note place="margin">VVhen ſinne hath the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie it flay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the man.</note> but alowe of it and conſent vnto it. If you yeelde your ſelues to obey, his ſeruauntes you are to whom you obey, whether it be of ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, or of obevieuce vnto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And this power of ſinne thus raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, doth teſtifie that the grace of Gods ſpirit is wanting. But if we ſtriue againſt our ſinne, if our eye be ſingle, that is, our minde vpright ſtriuing into the waye of the Lord without hypocriſie or diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though ſinne be in vs, yet our ſinnes are not of force to ſeparate vs from God, nor are any ſuch things as ſhall euer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, but for Chriſtes ſake (whoſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culier ſpirite hath wrought in vs this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking of ſinne, as ignoraunce, want of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Lords kindnes, and whatſoeuer of like ſort, with a longing alter the wayes of the Lorde) they are forgiuen vs, and ſhall neuer be layde to our charge, becauſe we beleeue in Chriſt. For the diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene heauen and earth is not ſo great, as is the difference betweene ſinne beeing
<pb facs="tcp:21049:39"/>in vs,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.20.</note> and ſinne raigning in vs, as maye appeare in that it is ſayde, Gal. 5.17. If therefore your ſinnes do diſpleaſe you,
<note place="margin">Theſe fruites of Chriſtes ſpirit aſſureth vs of the grace of Chriſt.</note> if you purpoſe to be an enimie to ſinne in your ſelfe and others, if you purpoſe to walke al your life in the true feare of God, and in the light of his worde, if you beleeue in Chriſt Ieſus for pardon of your ſinnes, and ſtay your ſelfe vpon his promiſes: I teſtifie vnto you, that you ſhall be a moſte welcome gueſt to this table of the Lorde. Chriſt hath already ſealed in you that you are deare in his ſight, he hath giuen you of his ſpirite,
<note place="margin">They that are leaſt in their owne ſighte, are moſte dear vvith the Lord.</note> and you ſhall haue fellowſhip with him, and with the father by him, and with the whole Church of God. Chriſte will dwell in you, and you ſhall dwell in him for euer, therefore meaſure not the Lords mercies by reaſon which is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, but let fayth holde faſt his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and be ioyfull in the Lorde, and from the grounde of a pure heart giue all prayle to him to whom all prayſe is due for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not the deed, but the maner of doing is al.</note> How many ſortes be there of them which receiue not the Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> There be two ſortes, namely thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:21049:39"/>that will not, and thoſe that can not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the eſtate of both?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The eſtate of the one, namely thoſe that can not, is not daungerous, for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the Sacramentes extendeth not ſo farre as to exclude them from eternall life which can not enioy the vſe therof, and thoſe that haue faith (which giueth them title and right to eternall life, and power to diſcerne rightly of the Sacramentes,) though they haue not the means to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Sacraments, ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued nor excluded from ſaluation.
<note place="margin">Their eſtate i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, vvhiche vvould and can not.</note> Alſo as this eſtate is not dangerous, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſuch as will not, namely of thoſe which contemne the Lords myſteries, is damnable. For it is vndoubtedly an act of infidelitie, and worthy of damnation,
<note place="margin">Their eſtate is damnable that can and vvill not.</note> for this and all wickednes proceedeth from vnbeliefe. For it is written, Take heede brethren, that there be not in any of you an euill heart and vnfaithfull,
<note place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note> to departe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the liuing God, &amp;c. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which eſtate of men the Lorde keepe all that be his for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21049:40"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A moſt godly and comfortable letter, written by by maiſter Edvvard Deering to a Chriſtian gentlevvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man beeing in heauineſſe of ſpirite, very needefull and (by the grace of Chriſt) helpfull, to ſuche as be in any meaſure in the like heauineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>JT is true (good maiſtres H.) which the Spirite hath ſpoken, and wee ſeele it by experience, that by many tribulations wee muſt enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is a common decree whiche God hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to be a let for all his children. So the author and finiſher of our faith, Ieſus Chriſte himſelfe was made perfect. Into his ſimilitude we are alſo predeſtinate, that we ſhould firſt die with him, &amp; then be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his glorie, Let vs not therefore refuſe that condition of life, in whiche we haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fellowſhip of al the Saints of God. But rather confeſſe with the holy Apoſtle, that bleſſed is the man who endureth temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But becauſe al afflictions are bitter for the preſent time, &amp; when the minde is ſhaken with ſorrowe, it is then moſte eaſily throwne downe of the enimie, let vs learne wiſely what our troubles are, and be prepa red of remedie in the day of triall. All our afflictions are ether according to the fleſhe in hunger, cold, nakednes, ſhame, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, ſlander, &amp;c. or according to the ſpirite, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations
<pb facs="tcp:21049:40"/>&amp; mournings, which the world knoweth not. The firſt euilles are eaſilie borne, for they are all but vanitie, and in vanity ther ſhall dye, if we ſee no fauour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of the Sun, that ſhire not heare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto vs: when we haue paide the debt we owe vnto death, the Lord then wil deliuer vs from al the iniuries of men. But in this behalfe let me confirme my ſelfe. God hath ſet you free from ſuch afflictions your goodes are vnto you in a liberal por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, your life made happie with a louing huſband, your calling acceptable vnder a gratious and good maiſtreſſe. In whoſe ſight you haue found fauour, In this eſtate you ſhall feele no trouble, therefore I let it paſſe. The other affliction, whithe is the ſpiritte, and whiche can not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted with anye earthlie bleſſing, looke for it aſſuredly, for it will come vnto you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you may ſuffer with Chriſt and reign with him in glorie, Theſe troubles they come many waies, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordingly as God doth leade vs into life. Firſt we are commanded to learne and knowe the worde of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this looke for many tentations, the enimy will try which way to plucke, that
<pb facs="tcp:21049:41"/>out of our hearts, out of the worde we muſt learn a pretious faith, &amp; hold that vmnoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before God, againſt this, what tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are betweene heauen and earth, you ſhall feele your portion, if any thing poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble can diſcourage you, with faith you muſt ioine a liuelie hope, which is a longing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gods glory, in this alſo Satan wil pretermit nothing to que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch your affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it may be dead &amp; to darken your mind y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you may ſee nothing, with out theſe you can not poſſiblie liue, &amp; vnto theſe you can not poſſblie come, but firſte you ſhall feele what is the ſtrength of ſinne. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding faint not, the Lion hath ouer come which is of the tribe of Iuda. The force of the Serpent ſhall bruſe our heele but it ſhall not take away from vs the head peece of ſaluation: Learn therefore, firſt the word of God, this is the ſeede of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by which we are made new creatures, this is the bread of ſpirituall nouriſhment, by which wee are growne vp into eternall life, This is the weapon of our warfare, by which we may wounde and driue away our enimies. This is the ſcepter of our glo rious kingdome, by which we do knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21049:41"/>God doth reign in vs. Take this vnto you, the ſhield of your defence, the ſtrengthe of your age, the wiſedome of your hearte, and the ſafetie of your life, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of Chriſt. Search y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scriptures, and ſeale it in your heart, with a good per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion that it is the word of God &amp; of life, and he hath grauen in it an expreſſe image of eternall trueth, Let it dwell plentifully within you, and your hart is armed with a moſt ſtrong defence, all enimies ſhall fall before it, the wiſedome of the wiſe ſhall be brought to nought, and the counſaile of the prudent ſhal be made fooliſhnes, the waies of the aduerſaries ſhall be ſcattered, and the ſcorners ſeate ſhall be thrown down, ſo true it is that the Lord hath ſpoken, Bleſſed is the man whoſe delight is in the law of the Lorde, and whoſe meditation is in it day &amp; night. Let vs then bring downe the hawti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our minds and receiue with meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word grafted in vs whiche can ſaue our ſoules, To this deſire of vnderſtanding when God hath brought vs, then let vs pray to be deliuered from tentation, &amp; take heed we be not ſpoiled of ſo great a treaſure, we haue three eſpecial enemies in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:42"/>of which S. Paule biddeth vs al be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, the one is Philoſophy, that is a vain &amp; curious ſearching of Gods miſteries, or meaſuring thinges reuealed according to our vnderſtanding, with which tentations whileſt our fathers were ouercome, they became fooliſh in their own imaginations and changed the glory of God into the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a corruptible man, making images, praying to angelles, immagining of ſoules like little children, deuiſing purgatorie, rea ſoning of Gods wiſeddme aboue our capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie. As if we be predeſtinate, we may liue as wee liſt, if we are commanded to worke, if our daies are numbred why ſeeke we any ſafetie to our life. If the Angels do keep vs in all our waies that we ſhall not hurt our foote againſt a ſtone, why feare we any fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: theſe phantaſies and worſe then theſe diſquiet our mindes and fight within vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our humble obedience to the worde of God, which all when we haue ouercome (and ſaid with the Prophet ſecrete things are for the Lorde: but thinges reuealed for vs and our children) yet we haue no peace, A ſecond enimie riſeth vp greater then the firſt, which S. Paul calleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> traditions of
<pb facs="tcp:21049:42"/>men, for the heart of man which drinketh in error as the grounde doth drinke water, is very obſtinately bound with old cuſtomes, and long continuaunce, meaſuring trueth which is pure &amp; holy, onely by time which is corrupt and euil, &amp; not only this, but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo hath inflamed our affections to loue to muche our fathers waies to like their opinions, to eſteeme their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to prayſe their doings, to commend their rage, to talk of their names, til throgh many entiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts we are at laſt bewitched, our wiſdome is ſtollen away, and trueth is taken from vs, by this meanes all corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which haue ouerflowed the earth haue ſtill wide roomes in the hearts of many the Popes ſupremacie, latine ſeruice, praier for the dead, Maſſes, diriges, pardons, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, ſenſing, &amp; all poperie, with the Authors of it, Popes, Cardinals, Monks, Friers, all which haue neither trueth, nor ſhadow of truth, not one word of them in al the goſpel of Chriſt, only old cuſtome hath bred it in our benes, &amp; an opinion of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hath printed it in our breſts &amp; we wil not caſt it out, but the Lorde be thanked who hath had mercie vppon vs to make,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:43"/>hold faſt the word of truth, what ſoeuer our fathers haue vainely taught vs, And yet we are not in ſecuritie. But a third enimie is in the hart of man, that the word of God may not haue his perfect honor, and that is an opinion conceiued of earthly thinges, &amp; planting of holines in corruptile creatures As in meates, drinkes, daies, garmentes, conditions of life, places, times, Cerimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, neither hearing our Sauiour Chriſt, that God is a ſpirite, and onelie he is to be worſhipped in ſpirite and trueth, neither his Apoſtle Paule, that the element of that world commend vs not vnto God, for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if we eate are wee euer the worſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if we eate not, are we euer the better. Theſe many and great tentations ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs aſſoone as wee woulde giue our ſelues to the word of God, which is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of a chriſtian life. Trowe you that in the continuance of our courſe and iorney before we come at our ſauiour Chriſt, ſhall we not be ſifted and tried, to ſee what is within vs. And you (good myſtreſſe H.) to apply this to your ſelfe, tell me howe you haue learned Chriſte, hath his goſpell bene peaceable in you, from the firſt day til now
<pb facs="tcp:21049:43"/>without all contradiction? was your minde neuer puffed vp in vaine imaginations, did the traditions and perſuaſions of men neuer ſhake your thought? haue you not ben te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opinions of creatures, as though ſome wer more holy, ſome more prophane: I knowe, as you long after Chriſt, &amp; deſire his trueth in ſingle heart: ſo his grace you haue not without ſharp &amp; bitter trials, and the more freely the word of God ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe your ſoule, and fill your hart full with all deſire of it, the more you ſhall feele what fight is againſte it, looke for the like in all your life, and when you approche to the true feare of God, prepare youre hearte to the ſtrongeſt aſſault. The word of God thus made knowen vnto vs, and when we follow it with all our ſoule, that we maye haue a liuely fayth to reioyce at the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God, to feare at his threatning, and feele a full perſwaſion of a certayne perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all his words. O Lorde what is the malice of Satan, and though many temptations are againſt vs, the long proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perities of the wicked in which they triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph whiles the goodnes of God prouoketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill to repentaunce, the bitter ſighing of
<pb facs="tcp:21049:44"/>the godly in which they mourne vnder ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny croſſes, whiles God maketh their fayth precious before him: theſe haue rooted quite out of the hearts of the vngodly, the fayth and truth which they owe vnto God, ſo that agaynſt all his iudgementes they haue opened their mouths and ſaid aloude: Where is the promiſe of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, and againſt all his mercies they haue proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med warre, and ſayde, they will not haue Chriſt to reigne ouer them. But theſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations Chriſt hath ouercome in vs, and giuen vs his ſpirite, in which we know aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly that the Lord reigneth, neither ſlac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth he his comming as many accounte ſlacknes, but he will come, and his glory ſhall be knownen. And yet we are not in peace, but Satan wil ſift vs another way, He will lay our ſinnes before vs, to make vs feare that the promiſes of God belong not vnto vs, and this of all temptations is the greateſt, yet we feare not, for what belongeth to all our ſinnes which Chriſte hath not borne? ſorowe, ſicknes, death, hel, condemnation, were they not in his body, and are they not all crucified vppon the Croſſe: Is he not riſen from them, and
<pb facs="tcp:21049:44"/>hath he not broken the chaynes of death, and ſo is aſcended vnto glory: If this be my feare becauſe I am a ſinner, rather let me reioyce, for Chriſt hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſinnes vpon him, and hath buried them deeper then the bottome of the ſea, he hath ledde it openly in triumph, and nayled it vppon the croſſe from henceforth and for euermore. It hath no ſtrength whoſoeuer ſecme to colour it as redde as ſcarlet, or make it like purple, it is ſtill nothing, and caſteth but a vayue terror before our eyes, we will neuer deny this, but freely confeſſe it, that we be miſerable ſinners, and not worthy to lifte vp our eyes to heauen, but who will lay our ſinnes to our charge, now god hath iuſtified vs: Or what ſinne can reſt vpon vs, now Chriſt hath waſhed them away: That which once was in fight with Chriſt and he hath ouercome it, who ſhall ſet to his hande the ſeconde time to make the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie perfect? This is true, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting trueth hath ſealed it vp, that ſinne is aboliſhed for euer and euer, howſoeuer we feare, or tremble, or be faynt harted, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde with whom our life is hid, there is no perill, no daunger, no fcare, but
<pb facs="tcp:21049:45"/>peace and righteouſnes without ende. Let our ſinnes be neuer ſo great, neither we nor our ſinnes can chaunge the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God is mercifull to our ſinnes, and will blot out all our tranſgreſſions, therefore this care is paſte, that our ſinnes be many, the more they are, the greater is his mercy who hath forgiuen them. And this is the token which God hath giuen vs that we are his, becauſe we are greeued with our ſinnes, for our Sauiour Chriſte ouercame ſinne, with paynes &amp; ſufferings which belong vnto it, and this is the badge of our redemption, to be made like him in afflictions, we haue ſinne, and abhorre it, it woundeth vs with feare, it ſetteth before vs condemnation, we haue a ſence and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Gods anger agaynſt it, and hell gnaweth vpon our ſoules becauſe of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. O bleſſed ſtate, and treaſure of gladnes, this was the image of Chriſt when he ouercame ſinne, a marke of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in my owne fleſh, that I ſhould not faynt. As the ſunne maketh the day, and the night darknes, ſo this affliction of ſinne is the badge and cogniſaunce of our
<pb facs="tcp:21049:45"/>certayne forgiuenes. And herein ſee the goodnes of God, which turneth all things to the beſt, to thoſe that loue him. Through feare of ſinne the diuell fighteth agaynſt vs: without feare of ſinne we could neuer haue boldnes: through anguiſh of heart the diuell woulde ouerwheline vs with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, without anguiſh of heart we coulde neuer haue ioye. In feeling Gods anger the diuel would make vs to diſpayre, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feeling his threatning and trembling before him, we could neuer haue ſtrength of fayth that his mercies are for euer. In all ſufferings I am like to Chriſt, they are the markes of mine addoption that I am hys childe, do we not heare the Lord: him ſelfe doth ſpeake, If we be without correction, then are we baſtardes and not ſonnes: and to ſhewe what our correction ſhall be, he ſayth in another place, If we be planted with him into the ſimilitude of his death, then ſhall we alſo be partakers of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Who hath heard ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as this: Euery weapon wherewith the enimie ſtriketh, the ſame armeth vs to greater ſaluation, and euery wounde that we do receiue, the ſame confirmeth vs to a
<pb facs="tcp:21049:46"/>ſuter life. (Then before as I ſayde) care not for ſinne, for that is aboliſhed: ſo here I may adde, Care not for hell, for the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer we feele it, the further we are from it. Let them feare ſinne that feele it not, and let them be afrayde of condemnation that knowe not what it is, vpon whom deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall come ſodenly as an armed man. Our eyes haue be kept waking, and we haue ſeene our ſinnes, our harts haue fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the anger of the Lorde, and wee haue not deſpiſed his heauenly calling, therefore in the daye of trouble we ſhall haue reſt. In this perſwaſion we will liue and dye, and if our ſoules ſhould melt for feare within vs, although the Lord ſhould kill vs, yet would we truſt in him. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham beleeued in the Lorde, and it was imputed vnto him for righteouſnes againſt hope, he beleeued vnder hope, and if our hoye ſeemed to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from vs, yet would we patiently wayte the Lordes leaſure vutill we ſaue our hope agayne, that at the leaſt our fayth might haue agayne, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and trueth of full aſſuraunce. An other thing we muſt labour in, and in an other thing we ſhall haue temptation, and that
<pb facs="tcp:21049:46"/>is, that we may ſee what is the glorie of God, and immortall life herein, lette vs meditate in our beddes, and thinke on this in our ſecret places, in the middeſt of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, let theſe cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be often in our heartes, and in all places let theſe be out m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes, when we ſhall apprehende with all the ſeruauntes of God what is the height, the bredth, the length, the depth, we ſhall know that the glory is great of immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and he is onely to be belecued, who ſhall ſhine in honour when this vanitie is ouerpaſt. His ſtrength is great that layde the foundations of the worlde, and bys brightnes exceeding that made the Sunne and the Moone. His treaſure and ritches are aboue meaſure, who hath giuen prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces their golde &amp; ſiluer and other precious ſtones for the honour of man, he in deed is of excellent maieſty, who is king of kings, &amp; Lord of Lords, &amp; his power is aboue all, who maketh ſickneſſe his meſſengers, and death his miniſter, till he ſhal aboliſh them both, for his mercies are vnſpeakable that forgineth vs all our ſinnes, &amp; his goodnes is great who hath had regard to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men. From nothing be brought vs
<pb facs="tcp:21049:47"/>into life, he kept vs from the graue, he wil reſtore vs &amp; make vs ſee his glory. When I would think on this, my ſoule is compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with dulnes of fleſh, that I cannot ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fulnes of his fauour. When I would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in my heart what is his grace, darknes ouerſhaddoweth mine vnderſtaning, &amp; all my thoughts do vaniſh in his immortality. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I would ſpeak of al his louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, my toung cleaueth to the roote of my mouth, and my words ſtick faſt within my lippes. But this one thing in al mine infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities I can perceiue, that his glorie is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great, whoſe glorie I can not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, &amp; the life is long, appointed vnto man where his heart and minde can ſee no end. If al the world were a flowing water, and euery yeare one drop ſhoulde be demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, the Sea ſhould be all made dry, and the bottomes of the deepe ſhoulde appeare, before he ſhall ceaſſe to liue, whome God hath raiſed from the dead, and this breadth &amp; wideneſſe betweene heauen and earth, if it ſhoulde be filled vp, and cuerie yeare but one handful of earth added to the work, yet ſooner ſhould y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great diſtance be cloſed vp &amp; the emptie places made full, then he ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:21049:47"/>ceaſe from ioy and gladnes, who ſhal ſtand in the reſurrection of the iuſt. This is the glorie that hath neither ſpot nor blemiſhe, before which me thincketh, not only prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe &amp; the glory of the world, but the Sun and Moone &amp; all the hoſtes of heauen, are nothing elſe but meere vanitie, for death ſhaddoweth the glorie of man, though hee ſpread his branches neuer ſo farre, yet the graue cloſeth vp in little roome the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart which before was enlarged from Eaſt to Weſt. And the heauens that are high &amp; free from death, yet are holden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tyranny of enuious and conſuming time, in which they ſhall be changed: onely the Lorde is in honour and maieſtie, who hath ſet eternity rounde aboute him, &amp; caſt out time vnto confuſion. Oh Lorde: where are their eyes that ſay not this, or their hearts that ſee and regard it not: who hath be witched them in the countenances of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to carry the hearts of beaſts, and to forget the latter ende: The Lord turne them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> run aſtray y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they may know &amp; ſee wher is their glorie, but the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations haue ouertaken them which are againſt our hope, when the Lord ſhall deliuer them from euil, they ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:21049:48"/>giue thee thankes and reioice with vs that they alſo haue eyes to ſee. And bleſſed are you good myſtres, H. and God hath viſited you in an acceptable time, whoſe heart he hath touched with feare, &amp; whoſe affections he hath filled with hunger and thirſt, that you ſhould mourn for the redemption that is in Chriſte, and be pleaſed with nothing but with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of his countenance. This is a ſchoolmyſtres to bring you vnto him, &amp; a bond to tye you faſt, that you ſhal not be ſeperate, And accompliſhe I beſeeche you this good worke of his grace, till you loue the Lorde withall your heart, and till you can ſay with the bleſſed Apoſtle I deſire to be deſolued and to be with Chriſt. For this purpoſe we are chaſtiſed of the Lorde, and when our faith is tried at the laſt it ſhall be made ſtrong, that w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it wee may quench al the firie darts of Sattan, and in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and peace, and ioy of the holy Ghoſt, runne the courſe that is ſet before vs, till in a bleſſed iſſue of happy daies, with a good ſpirite wee maye ſay boldly, Lorde, nowe letteſt thou thy ſeruaunte departe in peace, whiche I beſeeche GOD the father,
<pb facs="tcp:21049:48"/>of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the God of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and Father of all conſolation graunte vnto you. Amen.</p>
            <closer>Pray, pray, pray, pray, this is your beſt ſeruice whereſoeuer your duetie is moſt bounde.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
